<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Oaktree Howard Marks Memos (Full-Text via PDF, Unofficial)</title>
    <link>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/</link>
    <description>Automatic full-text RSS for Howard Marks memos. Personal use only.</description>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 10:45:38 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://tomdhyang-byte.github.io/oaktree-memo-rss/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>The Best of . . .</title>
      <link>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of</link>
      <guid>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of</guid>
      <pubDate>Invalid Date</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[To celebrate 35 years of my memos, I’m thrilled to release this collection of the ones I think are the best.]]&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded>&lt;![CDATA[ 





	
		
			
				PDF Translations
				
			
			
				&lt;ul&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
			
		
	



	
		
			
				
					
						
							
								
									
										
											Memos from Howard Marks
											Oct 12, 2025
										
									
									
										
											
											
											
										
									
								
								

									&lt;ul&gt;
											&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;PDF (English)&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;
										
																				&lt;li&gt;
											&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memos" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Archived Memos&lt;/a&gt;
										&lt;/li&gt;

									&lt;/ul&gt;

									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/email-alerts" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt;
								
							
						
						
							The Best of . . .
							&lt;br /&gt;
							&lt;br /&gt;
							
							
							&lt;p&gt;To celebrate 35 years of my memos, I’m thrilled to release this collection of the ones I think are the best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;These memos fall primarily into two categories. Some set out what I consider the enduring truths of investing – from the need for second-level thinking to the importance of risk control, the inevitability of cycles, and the futility of macro forecasting. Others chronicle the most impactful financial events of the last three decades: the dot-com bubble, the Global Financial Crisis, and the sea change in interest rate policy that took place in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing the memos is an absolute joy for me. They serve as the vehicle through which I share my thinking with the investment community, allow me to connect with Oaktree’s clients and employees, and serve as my creative outlet. I plan to keep at it. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Howard Marks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;October 12, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/1990-10-12-the-route-to-performance.pdf?sfvrsn=33bc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Route to Performance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 12, 1990&lt;/strong&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Route to Performance&lt;/em&gt; is the first memo I wrote. It articulates what would later become a core part of Oaktree’s investment philosophy: that long-term investment success is best achieved through a string of consistently good returns and an absence of poor years, rather than by aiming for brilliant successes, getting there in some years and flopping in others. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/1991-04-11-first-quarter-client-performance.pdf?sfvrsn=d7bd0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Quarter Performance &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 11, 1991&lt;/strong&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter of 1991, markets swung from extreme pessimism toward more reasonable sentiment, leading to excellent performance for sub-investment grade credit. The pendulum-like fluctuation between optimism and pessimism, fear and greed, and risk tolerance and risk aversion remains one of the most dependable features of the investment world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/1995-05-26-how-the-game-should-be-played.pdf?sfvrsn=d3bd0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How the Game Should Be Played&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 26, 1995&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using sports metaphors to illustrate Oaktree’s investment philosophy, I describe how our “game plan” is directed at avoiding strikeouts and achieving a high batting average over time, not at swinging for the fences on every trip to the plate. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2000-01-02-bubble.pdf?sfvrsn=37bc0f65_5" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;bubble.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 2, 2000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was the first of my memos to engender any response from readers! It describes the psychology of market bubbles in the context of a dot-com boom that would shortly become a dot-com bust when equity valuations fueled by excessive belief in the “the new, new thing” fell back to earth. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2001-07-11-whats-it-all-about-alpha.pdf?sfvrsn=13bc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s It All About, Alpha?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 11, 2001&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this memo, I reconcile the investment theory I was taught at the University of Chicago with the reality I encountered in the real world. I provide my take on alpha, beta, risk and return, and, most importantly, market efficiency – and the key implications for investors. If you swallow the efficient market hypothesis, you shouldn’t be an active investor. But if you ignore it, you’re likely to make critical mistakes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2001-11-20-you-cant-predict-you-can-prepare.pdf?sfvrsn=bc00f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You Can’t Predict. You Can Prepare.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 20, 2001&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is my first memo focused on the importance of economic and market cycles and the limits on knowledge of the macro future. It outlines a concept that permeates all Oaktree investment activity: we may never know where we’re going, but we ought to know where we are, and that knowledge of today’s environment should determine our response. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2002-05-31-the-realists-creed.pdf?sfvrsn=1bbc0f65_5" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Realist’s Creed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 31, 2002&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo serves as an acknowledgement that “I don’t know” is often the only reasonable refrain. It encourages investors to eschew macro forecasts and instead focus their attention on evaluating fundamentals and developing specialized expertise. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2002-11-11-returns-and-how-they-get-that-way.pdf?sfvrsn=4fbc0f65_8" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Returns and How They Get That Way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 11, 2002&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here I express my view as to where equity returns come from – either growth in earnings or an upgrading of how investors value those earnings – and my belief that relying on the latter might not work in the long run. I also provide my thoughts on a tougher question; how to judge whether a manager truly possesses skill given the presence of significant randomness in the investment world. You can guess what I look for: a long record of consistent but possibly modest outperformance, rather than occasional flashes of brilliance. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2003-09-05-whats-your-game-plan.pdf?sfvrsn=7bbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Your Game Plan?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 5, 2003&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was my second memo dedicated to the parallels between investing and sports, employing anecdotes from tennis and baseball and emphasizing Oaktree’s motto from the beginning: “if we avoid the losers, the winners will take care of themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2004-05-07-us-and-them.pdf?sfvrsn=bfbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Us and Them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 7, 2004&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo highlights the contrast between two styles of investors: the “I know” school – confident, aggressive, and forecast-driven, and the “I don’t know” school – consistent, risk-conscious, and focused on fundamentals. I look closely at personality types, attitudes toward the market, and other aspects of these investment styles. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2004-10-06-hedge-funds-a-case-for-caution.pdf?sfvrsn=57bc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hedge Funds: A Case for Caution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 6, 2004&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I set out my thoughts on the hedge fund movement – the hot topic in the investment world at the time – looking at aspects such as scalability and performance. Importantly, I say, nobody should credit any asset class (including hedge funds) with the birthright of a return. It all comes down to whether mispriced investment opportunities are available and whether the investor has the skill required to identify them. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2006-01-19-risk.pdf?sfvrsn=afbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 19, 2006&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I discuss what risk really means (not volatility!), why it matters, how to think about measuring it, and much more. Ultimately, it’s investors’ job to bear risk in the pursuit of profit. To do so wisely, they must understand risk and, of course, ascertain that they’re well compensated before deciding to bear it. But they can’t simply avoid it and hope for great returns. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2006-09-07-dare-to-be-great.pdf?sfvrsn=b3bc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dare to Be Great&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 7, 2006&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the first and most fundamental decisions for investors is with regard to the question of how far out on a limb they’ll venture. This memo reflects my thoughts on how investment management clients might best pursue superior results. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2006-10-19-the-new-paradigm.pdf?sfvrsn=8bbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The New Paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 19, 2006&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this memo, I discuss what can happen to managers’ motivations when vast sums become available for management in an asset class, with the accompanying ballooning of potential management fees. Looking at developments in buyout funds, the real estate market, and credit investing, I conclude that it’s a good time for increased caution. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2006-12-07-pigweed.pdf?sfvrsn=bbbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pigweed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;December 7, 2006&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A memo about the meltdown of a hedge fund called Amaranth Advisors, in which I parse the events surrounding its collapse. The fund had been making aggressive bets, and its successes were mistaken for long-term skill instead of than the reality: short-term luck. As usual, the prospect of exceptional profit earned with limited risk turned out to be a chimera. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2007-02-14-the-race-to-the-bottom.pdf?sfvrsn=9bbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Race to the Bottom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February 14, 2007&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo describes what happens when investors have too much money to invest and they’re too eager to put it to work. It represents a timely warning about the capital market behavior that ultimately led to the subprime mortgage meltdown of 2007 and the ensuing Global Financial Crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2007-07-16-its-all-good.pdf?sfvrsn=8fbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s All Good&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 16, 2007&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The “all-good trilogy” offers a reminder that good times are unlikely to last forever. In &lt;em&gt;It’s All Good&lt;/em&gt;, I highlight a few worrisome developments I’d spotted in the market: excessive use of leverage, untested securitization structures, and too-easy access to capital. We all know what happened next. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2007-07-30-its-all-good-really.pdf?sfvrsn=97bc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s All Good… Really?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 30, 2007&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this sequel, I describe how the events of July 2007 exemplify the elements that usually serve to initiate the swing back of the market pendulum. It’s important to study the way it happened, because while it’s folly to think we can know in advance what will cause the market to stop swinging in one direction and start in the other, it’s even more unwise to think that time-honored pattern won’t repeat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2007-09-10-now-its-all-bad.pdf?sfvrsn=9fbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now It’s All Bad?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 10, 2007&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just six weeks later, I discussed how rapidly market sentiment had shifted. In this case, a cascade of negative events – coming on top of too much leverage and not enough liquidity – led to a complete reversal of investor psychology. Before the collapse, some market participants believed they’d tamed risk. Well, risk bit back. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2008-10-15-the-limits-to-negativism.pdf?sfvrsn=fbbc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Limits to Negativism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 15, 2008&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This record of the fickleness of investor psychology was written very close to the absolute bottom in the investor sentiment. It describes the violent collapse of investor psychology that followed the bankruptcy of Lehman Brothers, bringing on the Global Financial Crisis. The environment from 2003-07 had been one of excessive positivity, but in 2008 I found it impossible to make assumptions negative enough to satisfy some onlookers. This excessive negativity signaled to me that there were vast opportunities for the stalwart contrarian. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2008-12-17-volatility-leverage-dynamite.pdf?sfvrsn=c7bc0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volatility + Leverage = Dynamite&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;December 17, 2008&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was levered mortgage-backed securities that were mostly responsible for the Global Financial Crisis, and I wrote this memo to explain that the amount of leverage it’s prudent to use is largely a function of the riskiness and volatility of the assets it’s used to purchase and the staying power of the asset holder. The combination of risky assets and excessive leverage under the wrong circumstances can prove fatal. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2010-12-17-all-that-glitters.pdf?sfvrsn=3bb0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All That Glitters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;December 17, 2010&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo incorporated all my thoughts about investing in gold. I outlined its pros and cons but ended up expressing the view that there’s no way to quantify the intrinsic value of assets like gold that don’t produce cash flow, and thus no way to invest in them analytically. Gold has worked as a store of value solely because people agreed it would. That’s not much of a foundation for a prudent investment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2012-03-19-déjà-vu-all-over-again.pdf?sfvrsn=bbb0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Déjà Vu All Over Again&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 19, 2012&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An exploration of the importance of historical awareness in prudent investing. The lessons of history are regularly forgotten when market sentiment becomes excessively optimistic or pessimistic. As these are the best times for applying a contrarian approach, ignoring historical patterns can be dangerous. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2012-06-20-its-all-a-big-mistake.pdf?sfvrsn=17bb0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s All a Big Mistake&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 20, 2012&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s rarely understood that for a buyer to make a bargain purchase, the seller has to sell too cheap. This memo explains that buying at a fair price doesn’t generate alpha – it’s buying at an unreasonably low one that does. Thus, accessing a bargain requires cooperation from someone who’ll sell at a price that’s irrationally low . . . but don’t despair; sometimes they do. We must try to be the one who profits from these mistakes rather than the one who commits them! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2013-03-13-the-outlook-for-equities.pdf?sfvrsn=6fbb0f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Outlook for Equities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 13, 2013&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The defining difference between bonds and stocks is that you can’t compute prospective returns for the latter. One of the few reliable indicators I find for prospective equity returns is that the better returns have been in the recent past, the less good they’re likely to be in the near future. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2014-01-16-getting-lucky.pdf?sfvrsn=c4b70f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting Lucky&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 16, 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this memo, the most popular through that time, I emphasize how big a part luck plays in both life and investing. This challenges the idea that success is always the result of hard work and skill and highlights the importance of acknowledging factors beyond one’s control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2014-04-08-dare-to-be-great-ii.pdf?sfvrsn=44b60f65_6" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dare to Be Great II&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 8, 2014&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building on &lt;em&gt;Dare to Be Great&lt;/em&gt;, written eight years earlier, this memo reiterates that unconventional behavior is the only route to superior investment results, although it’s far from sure to work. To engage in it, you have to dare to be different, dare to be wrong, and dare to look wrong for a while even when you’re right. This isn’t easy, and that’s why not everyone can take the steps needed for investment superiority. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2015-06-08-risk-revisited-again.pdf?sfvrsn=7bb70f65_8" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Revisited Again&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 8, 2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A treatise on the essence of investment risk, this memo stresses that whereas in our world risk is often defined as volatility, it really ensues from the fact that there is a range of possible outcomes from every investment, and it can include some that might be unpleasant. Importantly, risk can’t be reduced to a number and managed by algorithm. Doing a superior job of it requires superior insight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2015-09-09-its-not-easy.pdf?sfvrsn=47bb0f65_7" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s Not Easy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 9, 2015
                &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Charlie Munger told me, “none of this is easy.” I used that phrase as the title for a memo stressing that superior investing requires superior insight, plus the willingness to deviate from the herd, the ability to control one’s emotions, and an unrelenting emphasis on the defining role of price in investment decisions. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/on-the-couch.pdf?sfvrsn=8a1e0165_7" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Couch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 14, 2016
                &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo was my attempt to send the markets for a visit to the physiatrist and explore what might be learned there, analyzing investors’ irrationality and discussing why many of the things that seem obvious to most investors so often turn out to be wrong. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/what-does-the-market-know.pdf?sfvrsn=cb7a0165_10" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Does the Market Know?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 19, 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When people responded to &lt;em&gt;On the Couch&lt;/em&gt; by asking whether I was sure the market wasn’t sending a sell signal, I addressed the error of taking advice from the market. Most of the time, the market’s short-term behavior stems from irrational swings of investor perception “from hopeless to flawless,” rather than a dispassionate weighing of merit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/this-time-its-different.pdf?sfvrsn=fc19af65_10" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This Time It’s Different&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 12, 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In good times, the notion that “this time it’s different” often works its way into the marketplace as investors use it to justify soaring prices for popular assets. This sentiment can be expressed in contexts ranging from questioning the possibility of a recession to supporting the high valuations of unproven companies dealing in the latest miracle. This memo discusses the outlook for nine such theories and how things would truly have to be different for them to prove out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/you-bet.pdf?sfvrsn=785dbe65_8" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You Bet!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 13, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here I build on the counterintuitive principle that you can’t tell the quality of a decision from its outcome, and that the presence of randomness means well-thought-out decisions may fail and poor decisions may succeed. In investing, superior skill will overcome the impact of luck in the long run, but in the short run, luck can swamp skill, and the two can be indistinguishable. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/uncertainty.pdf?sfvrsn=d913b465_28" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 11, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Against the confounding backdrop of the Covid-19 pandemic, a reminder that forecasting is futile and we must admit the limitations on our knowledge. The things we know about the macro environment generally are of no use in gaining an edge – because everyone else knows them too! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/uncertainty-ii.pdf?sfvrsn=d48a65_8" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncertainty II&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 28, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo builds on &lt;em&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/em&gt; as the pandemic continues to rage, but with an important addition: not only do most people lack sufficient expertise to achieve superiority, but they also lack the expertise needed to identify which “experts” do possess it. While individuals often seek comfort in the output of reputable forecasters, they usually end up disappointed but rarely acknowledge the core problem: that macro forecasts are seldom helpful. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/something-of-value " rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something of Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 11, 2021&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Something of Value&lt;/em&gt;, I say how valuable it was to have my son Andrew and his family move in with us during the pandemic, and I highlight the seeming divide between “value” and “growth” investing as a potentially false dichotomy. In an investment environment marked by fewer bargains and greater efficiency than the one I grew up in, value investors shouldn’t limit themselves to bottom-fishing and instead should expand their toolbox and think about ‘‘winners” too. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/i-beg-to-differ " rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I Beg to Differ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 26, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo returns to the idea that investors seeking superior performance must have the courage to depart from the pack. Thinking differently and better than others is essential, because to outperform in investing, it’s not enough to be right. You have to be more right than most. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-illusion-of-knowledge" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Illusion of Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 8, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A huge number of factors must be correctly predicted in order for a macro forecast to be accurate. As no forecast can be better than the ability of its algorithm to capture the workings of an incredibly complex world, why would anyone expect their forecast to be more accurate than the rest? &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/what-really-matters" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Really Matters?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;November 22, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo argues that short-term performance, hyperactivity, and volatility don’t matter; instead, what I call “asymmetry” is the cornerstone of investing excellence. Superior investors achieve success by delivering returns that are more than commensurate with the risk they bear. This requires superior skill and insight, attributes that only the best possess. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/sea-change" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sea Change&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;December 13, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hopefully a seminal memo, &lt;em&gt;Sea Change&lt;/em&gt; reviews the impact of 40 years of declining interest rates, brought to a halt by the need to fight post-pandemic inflation. This leads to an important observation: when the investing environment undergoes fundamental change, one’s strategy must undergo a thorough review. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/taking-the-temperature" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taking the Temperature &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 10, 2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A look back at my five main market calls. Making such calls isn’t common practice for me, but I made each of the five because I found the market crazily elevated or depressed. They weren’t based on crunching financial data or on expertise regarding the specific investments in question, but on the clear-eyed assessment of investor psychology. Having identified these extremes, I felt comfortable calling for an adjustment of Oaktree’s risk posture. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/fewer-losers-or-more-winners" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fewer Losers, or More Winners?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 12, 2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the pursuit of superior risk-adjusted returns (or winning tennis), a participant’s game plan requires choosing between the two main paths: either experiencing fewer losers or finding more winners. I argue that in credit, having fewer losers will generally serve best, but smart credit investing should be based on risk control, not risk avoidance. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-indispensability-of-risk" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indispensability of Risk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 17, 2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With investors facing intelligent competitors, as we do every day, no one should expect to achieve significant returns without bearing risk. But they also shouldn’t expect to achieve them simply for bearing risk. It has to be done consciously and skillfully.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/ruminating-on-asset-allocation" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruminating on Asset Allocation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;October 22, 2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This memo offers my articulation of the fundamental difference between equity and debt: a generous but uncertain expected return with both upside and downside potential from the former, versus a more modest contractual return accompanied by much less uncertainty from the latter. This difference is the essential consideration in portfolio construction, in which investors must determine their appropriate risk posture and combine ownership and lending assets in a portfolio that gets them there. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Calculus of Value&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;August 13, 2025
                &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An assessment of the essence of value and price and the critical relationship between the two. I argue that in the long run, increases in value – usually stemming from growth in earnings – provide most of the impetus for investment returns, and value exerts a magnetic influence on price. That means the current relationship of price to value should be expected to strongly influence future investment performance, with high valuations presaging low subsequent returns, and vice versa. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal Information and Disclosures&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum expresses the views of the author as of the date indicated and such views are subject to change without notice. Oaktree has no duty or obligation to update the information contained herein. Further, Oaktree makes no representation, and it should not be assumed, that past investment performance is an indication of future results. Moreover, wherever there is the potential for profit there is also the possibility of loss.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum is being made available for educational purposes only and should not be used for any other purpose. The information contained herein does not constitute and should not be construed as an offering of advisory services or an offer to sell or solicitation to buy any securities or related financial instruments in any jurisdiction. Certain information contained herein concerning economic trends and performance is based on or derived from information provided by independent third-party sources. Oaktree Capital Management, L.P. (“Oaktree”) believes that the sources from which such information has been obtained are reliable; however, it cannot guarantee the accuracy of such information and has not independently verified the accuracy or completeness of such information or the assumptions on which such information is based.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum, including the information contained herein, may not be copied, reproduced, republished, or posted in whole or in part, in any form without the prior written consent of Oaktree.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;© 2025 Oaktree Capital Management, L.P.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
						
						
							
								

Share
 &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of&amp;text=Oaktree Capital: The Best of . . .:%20https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/shareArticle?mini=true&amp;url=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of/%2F&amp;title=Oaktree Capital: The Best of . . .&amp;summary=&amp;source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of/%2F&amp;quote=Oaktree Capital: The Best of . . ." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:?subject=Oaktree Capital: The Best of . . .&amp;body=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-best-of" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
								
							

						
					
				
			
		
	













	
		
			
				
					
						&lt;h2&gt;Related Content&lt;/h2&gt;
					
					
						
							
									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo-podcast/35-years-of-memos" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/hm_memo_podcast.png?sfvrsn=61247366_3" alt="35 Years of Memos for audio" /&gt;memosOct 12, 202535 Years of MemosListen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo-video/celebrating-35-years-of-memos-with-howard-marks" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/35-years-of-memos-video.png?sfvrsn=6c0a2966_1" alt="Celebrating 35 Years of Memos with Howard Marks for video" /&gt;memosOct 12, 2025Celebrating 35 Years of Memos with Howard MarksWatch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/the-memo-from-howard-marksd198ddb3-6ceb-4922-8cac-9ddfca1ae261.png?sfvrsn=7bfc7366_1" alt="The Calculus of Value for article" /&gt;memosAug 14, 2025The Calculus of ValueRead&lt;/a&gt;


								
								
									
										
											Load More
										
									
								
							
						
					

				
			

		

	
	
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="javascript:openPDF('The Best of. . .','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/the-best-of.pdf?sfvrsn=e40a2966_4')" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Download PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</content:encoded>
      <enclosure url="javascript:openPDF('The Best of. . .','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/the-best-of.pdf?sfvrsn=e40a2966_4')" type="application/pdf"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Calculus of Value</title>
      <link>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value</link>
      <guid>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value</guid>
      <pubDate>Invalid Date</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[On July 28, I flew to South America on a plane without Wi-Fi, leaving me without email or entertainment.  What was I to do but start in on a memo?  Interestingly, the things I wrote during that flight turned out to be the answers to many...]]&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded>&lt;![CDATA[ 





	
		
			
				PDF Translations
				
			
			
				&lt;ul&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Japanese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Korean
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Simplified Chinese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Traditional Chinese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
			
		
	



	
		
			
				
					
						
							
								
									
										
											Memos from Howard Marks
											Aug 14, 2025
										
									
									
										
											
											
											
										
									
								
								

									&lt;ul&gt;
											&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;PDF (English)&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;
																					&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a href="#" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;PDF (Translations)&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;

											&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo-podcast/the-calculus-of-value" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Listen to Memo&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;
																				&lt;li&gt;
											&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memos" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Archived Memos&lt;/a&gt;
										&lt;/li&gt;

									&lt;/ul&gt;

									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/email-alerts" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt;
								
							
						
						
							The Calculus of Value
							&lt;br /&gt;
							&lt;br /&gt;
							
							
							&lt;p&gt;On July 28, I flew to South America on a plane without Wi-Fi, leaving me without email or entertainment.  What was I to do but start in on a memo?  Interestingly, the things I wrote during that flight turned out to be the answers to many of the questions I received from clients after I landed, so writing what follows served me well.  I hope it’ll do the same for you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;*            *            *&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 2 of this year was the 25th anniversary of my memo &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2000-01-02-bubble.pdf?sfvrsn=37bc0f65_5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;bubble.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the one that put my writing on the map, and I marked the occasion by publishing another memo, called &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/on-bubble-watch" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Bubble Watch&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. While the title may have raised concern for readers, my main conclusion was that the elevated U.S. stock market valuations at the time didn’t necessarily signal the existence of a bubble, mainly because I didn’t detect the extreme investor psychology I associate with bubbles.  Security prices were “lofty but not nutty” is how I put it.  Because a lot has taken place in the seven months since then, it’s time for an update on asset values.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before I start, please note that I’m talking about investing in general.  My specific reference will be to public U.S. corporate securities – stocks and bonds – since they mark to market regularly and are the assets that most enter my consciousness.  But since investors’ actions toward one group of assets and the resulting price movements influence other assets and other markets – and since they ensue largely from investor psychology, which is highly contagious – I think my comments are probably applicable to other asset classes, to private assets as well as public ones, and possibly to markets outside the U.S. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll start by laying out where I think investment value comes from and how it should be assessed.  I don’t think I’ve ever done this before in this form.  It’s a big topic, but I’ll try to cover it briefly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Value&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investment assets – things such as stocks, bonds, companies, and buildings – have a value, which is sometimes referred to as their “intrinsic value”:&lt;/strong&gt; what the asset is “worth” at a point in time.  This value is subjective.  It can’t definitively be found anywhere – not even by AI, as far as I know – and opinions will differ as to what it is.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my parlance, the value of an asset is derived from its “fundamentals.”  The fundamentals of a company, for example, encompass a great many things.  These include its current earnings, its earning power in the future, the steadiness or variability of its future earnings, the market value of its component assets, the skill of management, its potential to develop new products, the competitive landscape, the strength of its balance sheet, and the myriad additional factors that will influence the company’s future.  &lt;strong&gt;Ultimately, the totality of an asset’s fundamentals constitute its earning power, which in turn is the source of its value.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A company may own land, buildings, machinery, vehicles, and natural resources such as mineral deposits or forests, and even facilities that allow it to derive electricity from river water or sunshine (which it obviously doesn’t own).  These are tangible assets, and there’s often a market for them and a realizable price.  But a company may also have assets that are intangible, such as patents, trade secrets, knowhow, research capability, reputation and image, human talent, management skill, and culture.  Some of these may be transferable and salable, but others are not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All the assets mentioned above have earning power individually, and in combination they create a company’s overall earning power.  &lt;/strong&gt;A company’s earning power almost always exceeds the sum of the earning power of each of its individual assets taken in isolation.  Combining individual assets to maximize a company’s overall earning power is the top job of management.  When successful, the result is synergy: the benefit gained from skillfully combining things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;But not all assets have earning power (as I define it), and thus not all have calculable investment value.  I describe earning power as the money you can make by owning and operating an asset – that is, I omit from “earnings” the possible gains from simply holding an asset and ultimately selling it.  A diamond ring, painting, or classic car doesn’t produce earnings for its owner (short of renting it out or charging people to look at it).  For this reason, its economic potential comes exclusively from the possibility of selling it at a profit.  And the person who buys it is likely to be doing so in the hope of selling it to someone else at a still-higher price . . . despite the fact that it won’t produce earnings in the interim.  &lt;strong&gt;I think of assets that don’t produce operating cash flow or have the potential to do so in the future as not having earning power, and that makes them impossible to value objectively, analytically, or intrinsically&lt;/strong&gt; (see my 2010 memo about gold, &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2010-12-17-all-that-glitters.pdf?sfvrsn=3bb0f65_6" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;All That Glitters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some earning power is current and produces income today.  The result can be seen in this year’s financial statements: the income that today’s assets are producing in their current configuration and under today’s conditions.  Other earning power exists in the form of potential: for example, the income that will be earned when today’s holdings of natural resources are exploited in the future, or the income that will be generated from new products developed by the company’s employees from its intellectual property.  The result will be dependent on the environment that unfolds, which in turn will be influenced by decisions made by company management, competitors, customers, governments, and even investors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assets can be tangible or intangible, and an asset’s earning power can produce earnings today and also in the future in amounts that might be higher or lower than today.  Together, an asset’s current earnings, plus its power to produce earnings in the future, constitute its key fundamentals.  &lt;/strong&gt;Some investors emphasize paying a reasonable price for today’s earning power, and others are willing to bet on what they see as potential growth in earning power.  &lt;strong&gt;Regardless, I think prudent investing has to be based on judgments regarding an asset’s present and future earning power.  Once an investor has determined an asset’s intrinsic value in this way, he will have a basis for establishing a “right” price that will allow for good returns in the future.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Price&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;While value can seem theoretical and ephemeral, price is concrete.  It’s the amount you pay to obtain something.  &lt;/strong&gt;Ultimately, as indicated above, doing a good job of investing comes down to estimating value appropriately and purchasing that value at a reasonable price.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, there are a great many things that combine to make up an asset’s fundamentals.  Ultimately, they can be boiled down to its earning power, and it’s from earnings that value is derived.  &lt;strong&gt;In the late 1960s, I was taught at the University of Chicago Graduate School of Business that the right price for an asset is the discounted present value of its future cash flows or earnings.  &lt;/strong&gt;You might object: What about all the other things listed above, such as a company’s plant and equipment, intellectual property, and management, and even its reputation? Don’t they have value?  The value of all of these things is derived from their ability to contribute to the company’s earning power, and thus it’s captured in the earnings calculation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key part of a security analyst’s job consists of arriving at earnings projections.  Then those projections have to be converted into a fair price.  At the University of Chicago, the discounting process was purely mathematical: you divide the earnings for each year in the future by (1+r)n, where r is the appropriate discount rate and n is the number of years out into the future the earnings are, and then you total up the yearly results.  &lt;strong&gt;But in the real world, price is set by a different discounting process, which consists mostly of people applying their subjective opinions and attitudes about what the asset and its earning power are worth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So that’s what an asset’s price is: the consensus view of investors regarding its underlying fundamental value.  &lt;/strong&gt;According to Benjamin Graham, the father of value investing and Warren Buffett’s teacher at Columbia, market prices are set each day by investors who cast their votes by offering to buy or sell.  Some investors think a company has a solid product line and competent management, and others consider it stodgy and outmoded.  Some investors find another company sexy and right for the future, and others think it’s a risky high-flyer.  These attitudes are converted into asset prices.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is where the tug-of-war comes in.  As I see it, every day with regard to every asset, the optimists do battle with the pessimists.  The market throws out, “GM at $52.”  The optimists think it’s worth $58, so they’re happy to buy at $52.  Since the pessimists think it’s only worth $46, they’re willing to accommodate the buyers by selling at $52, and a trade takes place.  But sometimes, one side or the other predominates.  If the people who think it’s worth $58 outnumber the ones who think it’s worth $46, more people will want to buy at $52 than want to sell there, so the price will rise to $53, and maybe $54, and so forth.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just as an imbalance of opinion in one direction or the other can move the price of GM, it can also move a whole market.  Sometimes the overall mood of investors in a market is positive, meaning they’re characterized by optimism, credulousness, fear of missing out (“FOMO”), and risk tolerance.  And sometimes the mood is negative and marked by pessimism, skepticism, fear of loss, and excessive risk aversion.  Whereas in real life things fluctuate between pretty good and not so hot, in the minds of investors things can go from flawless to hopeless and back.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When the majority of investors are optimistic, they cause price to rise and potentially exceed value.  And when the pessimists reign, they cause price to decline and potentially fall short of value.  &lt;/strong&gt;Thus, a preponderance of investor psychology on one side or the other – in lieu of the rationality and objectivity on which the Efficient Market Hypothesis is predicated – can create the bargains or over-pricings the hypothesis says can’t exist.  Investors should be on the lookout for them. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The price of an asset means nothing in isolation.  You can’t tell whether a car is good buy at $40,000 unless you know about the things that determine its market value: its make, model, age, mileage and condition.  &lt;strong&gt;It’s the same in investing; what matters is the relationship between an asset’s price and its value.  Investors call that relationship the asset’s “valuation.”  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Interaction of Price and Value&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If an asset is bought for the right price (or less), its current earnings can give the buyer a good return on his purchase price while he owns it, and increases in earning power can add to the current return it throws off and increase its value and thus the price at which it can be sold.  &lt;strong&gt;Thus, an investor’s ability to earn an attractive return on an investment will largely depend on whether he accurately appraised the investment’s fundamentals and paid an appropriate price for those fundamentals.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the long term, the success of an investment will hinge primarily on whether the buyer was right about the asset’s earning power.  &lt;/strong&gt;However, an asset’s current earning power and opinions regarding its future earning power usually don’t change much from month to month or even year to year.  &lt;strong&gt;Thus, short-term investment performance is likely to stem mostly from changes in the price investors are willing to pay for the asset.  That makes price the dominant consideration for anyone whose principal concern is the short run.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value should be thought of as exerting a “magnetic” influence on price.  &lt;/strong&gt;If price is above value, future price movements are more likely to be downward than upward.  And if price is below value, future price movements are more likely to be upward than downward.  &lt;strong&gt;However, in the short run, price can move in just about any direction relative to value.  &lt;/strong&gt;This is so because an asset’s price at any given point in time is mostly determined by investor psychology, which can be irrational and unpredictable.  &lt;strong&gt;Thus, while the current relationship of price to underlying value should move in the expected direction, it can only be counted on to do so in the long run at best.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“More likely to be” is the key phrase in the above paragraph.  &lt;/strong&gt;An undervalued asset can remain cheap – or even get cheaper – for a long time, just as an overvalued asset can become more overvalued, and then extremely overvalued, and then crazily overvalued.  It’s the ability of price to go to crazy extremes that causes bubbles and crashes.  If price always stopped going up when it began to exceed value, we wouldn’t have extended bull markets and bubbles (and the ensuing crashes), and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;People who bet heavily that price will move in the direction of value – which we call “converging” – can be carried out if they don’t have sufficient staying power.  That’s why John Maynard Keynes said, “The market can remain irrational longer than you can remain solvent.”  &lt;strong&gt;It’s intellectually sound to expect price to move toward value rather than diverge further from it, and even to bet that it will happen, but it’s unwise and potentially dangerous to bet heavily that it’ll happen soon.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Benjamin Graham said, in the short run the market functions like a voting machine, reflecting assets’ popularity.  But in the long run, it’s a weighing machine, assessing assets’ value.  &lt;strong&gt;Thus, we can think in terms of a “calculus of value” that I find entirely logical and almost mathematical . . . except for the fact that it’s applied by people who aren’t:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Value is what you get when you make an investment, and price is what you pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A good investment is one in which the price is right for what the value turns out to be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the volatile nature of investor psychology, asset prices fluctuate much more than fundamental value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus, most price changes reflect changes in investor psychology rather than changes in fundamental value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of the key role psychology plays in setting asset prices, in order to have a sense for where price stands relative to value, investors should try to gauge prevailing psychology, not just quantitative valuation parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The relationship of price to value should be expected to strongly influence investment performance, with high valuations presaging low subsequent returns, and vice versa.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But that relationship must not be counted on to have the expected impact in anything but a long-term sense.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the price of an asset is “fair” (however that’s assessed), it’s reasonable for an investor to expect to earn a return that is likewise fair for the risk borne, relative to the risk-adjusted returns on other assets.  But so-called “active investors” go to the trouble of studying companies and markets, buying some assets but not others, and overweighting some and underweighting others – and clients employ active investment managers and pay them fees – in the hope of earning returns that are more than fair for the risk borne and thus better than the risk-adjusted returns enjoyed by other investors.  (According to investment theory, investors can dependably earn a fair or average return by investing passively and thereby avoid paying active management fees.  But active investors want more.)  &lt;strong&gt;What conditions might give rise to the superior risk-adjusted returns active investors crave?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consensus of investors doesn’t fully comprehend the asset’s current value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The market price is too low for the current value of the asset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The asset’s value increases more than investors anticipated, usually because of an unforeseen increase in its earning power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The asset becomes more popular with investors, resulting in an increase in its price that is unrelated to changes in value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There may be additional possibilities, but I think the above list is pretty exhaustive.  And, of course, developments in the opposite direction from those described above can result in risk-adjusted returns that are inferior, including returns that are negative.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the absence of one or more of the conditions listed immediately above, there’s no reason to expect an investment to provide superior returns.  And even if these things are present, investors shouldn’t expect to achieve superior results unless they possess the superior insight needed to detect them.  In a nutshell, it’s helpful to think of returns as stemming from (a) changes in value and (b) changes in the relationship between price and value, and the people who earn superior returns are the ones who anticipate those changes better than others. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;How Do Investors Think About Price and Value?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you watch financial TV shows or read about the market in newspapers or investment publications, most of what you come across relates to price, or to the relationship between price and value.  The audience doesn’t go there to find out how good the company is or what its earning power will be in 2045.  They go there to be told whether stock prices will go up or down in the short run (that is, if they know to ask, whether the short-term return will be more or less than fair for the risk, and superior or inferior to the risk-adjusted returns on other assets).  And, of course, that’s mostly about price/value.  So where does that relationship stand today?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Like many things that are made up of a large number of ingredients both qualitative and quantitative, a company’s attributes can’t be summed up through an algorithm or reduced to a single number.  Evaluating them requires judgment.  And if the value of a company, for example, is multivariate and confusingly unquantifiable, it obviously can be very hard to assess the fairness of its price at a point in time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Equity investors deal with this challenge by looking primarily – often almost exclusively – at a stock’s p/e ratio, or the ratio of a company’s share price to the amount of earnings attributable to each share of its common stock.  It’s easy to calculate the p/e ratio for one stock or the average for a stock market or index, and thus to know how the current p/e ratio compares to p/e ratios on other stocks or at other points in time.  Deviations from those p/e norms are examined in light of the factors that distinguish the company from other companies (based on aspects of fundamentals beyond the current earnings) or that distinguish today from past times, and investors reach conclusions as to whether the asset is overpriced, fairly priced, or underpriced given those considerations.  Of course, basing an investment decision on a single metric, such as a stock’s p/e ratio, represents a vast oversimplification of the decision, and thus introduces the possibility of error.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting Up to Date&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now we can start getting current and concrete.  Where were we when 2025 began?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The S&amp;P 500 stock index is the most watched barometer of the U.S. stock market.  Toward the end of last year, its forward-looking p/e ratio (the ratio of its price to its estimated earnings over the coming year) was around 23, significantly above its historical average.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time, J.P. Morgan published a graph showing that if you bought the S&amp;P 500 index at 23 times the coming year’s earnings per share in the period 1987-2014 (the only period for which there’s data on forward-looking p/e ratios and resulting ten-year returns), your average annual return over the subsequent ten years was between plus 2% and minus 2% &lt;strong&gt;every time&lt;/strong&gt;. To the extent this p/e ratio history is relevant, it bodes pretty poorly for the S&amp;P 500.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I concluded in my January memo that this was troublesome but not threatening, again mostly because the temporary mania or “irrational exuberance” that I believe accompanies – or gives rise to – most bubbles wasn’t present.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That was then.  What has happened since?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. stock markets saw declines of up to 10% in the first quarter of this year, with the tech-heavy Nasdaq Composite falling the most.  This was primarily the result of unspectacular economic and corporate performance, moderate but still higher-than-desired inflation, and possibly worries about valuation levels and whether the U.S. would retain its position as the world’s investment destination of choice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, on April 2, President Trump announced tariffs on imported goods that were much higher and much more sweeping than had been anticipated.  Investors promptly concluded the tariffs were likely to cause inflation to accelerate, economic growth to slow, and the U.S. to be viewed less favorably by nations and investors around the world.  The result was a sharp drop in the S&amp;P 500, taking it to a level 15% lower than where it was at the end of 2024.  In short, investors determined the fundamental outlook had been impaired, and they took down stock prices in line with those poorer fundamentals.  Bond investors reacted as well, demanding a yield on the benchmark 10-year Treasury note that got as high as 4½%, up from just over 4% immediately before the tariff announcement.  Higher bond yields mean lower bond prices, and bond investors made clear that they thought the risks were higher and thus increased risk compensation was in order. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;But from the S&amp;P 500’s low point on April 8, it has risen by 29% through yesterday, putting it up by 9% for the year to date.  Much of this seems to have been a “relief rally,” with trade deal deadlines being extended and/or tariffs being established below April’s announced levels, and with inflation from tariffs not yet having materialized.  In short, the tariff picture thus far is less bad than was feared at the time of the original announcements.  It’s also possible that investors are encouraged by expectations of rising earnings; the tax and spending bill that was passed, with its favorable treatment of corporations; the pledges to invest in the U.S. that a number of foreign countries have made as part of trade deals; and even the potential of artificial intelligence to add to companies’ earning power.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What can we say about the price/value calculus today?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The S&amp;P 500 was highly valued at the end of 2024 and also just before the tariff announcement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The economic possibilities – and likely multi-year earning power for companies – are probably less positive on balance than they were before the tariff announcement, albeit not as bad as initially feared.  Rising inflation is still a concern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The threat of higher inflation has reduced the likelihood of the early, stimulative interest rate cuts investors had hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trade and tariff agreements the administration sought are being extracted, but the U.S. seems to be viewed around the world as a less-dependable ally and partner, and some investors may conclude they should be less heavily weighted toward U.S. assets.  Implementation of this view could cause net selling and/or reduce the future demand for these assets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. fiscal deficits and national debt show no sign of improvement, and worldwide concern over them seems to be increasing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, with the outlook possibly diminished on balance, U.S. stock prices are up.  While earnings are expected to rise, stock prices are up more.  Thus, regardless of where it stood as this year began, the value proposition in U.S. stocks seems to be less appealing today than it was at year-end – and even then, it wasn’t great.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are the indicators of investor behavior and the resulting price/value relationship?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The elevated p/e ratio on the S&amp;P 500 is the tentpole of the argument that valuations are optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt; (July 25), “Stocks in the S&amp;P 500 are now valued at more than 3.3 times their [companies’] sales, according to Bloomberg, an all-time high.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the same &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; article, “A Barclays ‘equity-euphoria indicator,’ a composite of derivative flows, volatility and sentiment, has surged to twice its normal level, into territory associated with asset bubbles.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffett’s favorite indicator – the ratio of the aggregate market capitalization of U.S. stocks to U.S. GDP – is also at an all-time high.  It’s especially worth noting that the U.S. market cap has been restrained by companies’ tendency to wait longer these days before going public and by the fact that many companies have been taken private in buyouts.  Thus, this elevated indicator could be even more troubling than it appears. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current relationship between the yield on the 10-year U.S. Treasury note and dividend yield on the S&amp;P 500 shows the latter to be expensive in historical terms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;So-called “meme stocks” – stocks favored by online retail investors, who don’t necessarily think in terms of the value proposition described above – have attracted heightened attention lately.  Many sport prices that seem low at first glance, but you have to wonder whether their buyers fully understand the companies’ fundamentals, some of which appear precarious.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yield spreads – the amount of incremental yield investors demand if they’re going to give up the safety of Treasury securities and buy corporate debt for its higher yields – are approaching all-time lows and are less generous than they were when I wrote the memo &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/gimme-credit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gimme Credit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in March.  This, too, implies an elevated level of risk tolerance on the part of investors, and thus is another sign of a lofty market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;An aside regarding the valuation of the S&amp;P 500:  A bit over half of its jaw-dropping 58% two-year total return in 2023-24 was attributable to the spectacular performance of just seven stocks, those of the so-called “Magnificent Seven” – Apple, Microsoft, Alphabet (parent company of Google), Amazon, Meta Platforms (parent company of Facebook), Nvidia, and Tesla.  These are great companies – some are the best companies ever – and these seven stocks have grown to represent a startling one-third of the total market value of the 500-stock index.  (Please bear in mind that I don’t claim to be an expert on stocks in general or tech stocks in particular.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of these companies’ greatness, their stocks are highly valued, and there’s a popular perception that their elevated valuations are responsible for the S&amp;P 500’s unusually high average p/e ratio.  The fact is their p/e ratios average out to roughly 33.  This is certainly an above average figure, but I don’t find it unreasonable when viewed against what I believe to be the companies’ exceptional products, significant market shares, high incremental profit margins, and strong competitive moats.  (A lot of the Nifty-Fifty stocks First National City Bank owned when I got there in 1969 were selling at p/e ratios between 60 and 90.  Now that’s high!)  &lt;strong&gt;Rather, I think it’s the average p/e ratio of 22 on the 493 non-Magnificent companies in the index – well above the mid-teens average historical p/e for the S&amp;P 500 – that renders the index’s overall valuation so high and possibly worrisome.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why are asset prices so strong in the face of what I view as net negative developments?  How can the S&amp;P 500 have risen 14% in the four-plus months since April 1, the day before the tariffs were announced, given that most observers believe the tariffs will add to inflation, weigh on economic growth, and reduce the perception of the U.S. as the premiere investment destination?  Here’s my explanation:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Investors are by nature optimistic.  You must be an optimist to hand over your money to someone else in the hope of getting more back later.  This is especially true of equity investors, and I think their optimism dies hard.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When they’re in an optimistic mood, investors have the ability to interpret ambiguous developments positively and overlook negatives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last sustained market correction ended in early 2009, meaning it’s been over 16 years since risk bearing was seriously punished and “buying the dips” wasn’t rewarded.  That means no one under 35 or so – professional and amateur investors alike – has ever experienced a prolonged bear market.  Older investors have experienced one or more, but, with the passage of such a long time, some may have been lulled into a false sense of security. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the U.S. probably continues to offer the best investment fundamentals in the world, some investors may not appreciate the possibility that it’s a little “less best.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rationalizations often emerge to keep bull markets going.  One these days is “TACO,” which stands for “Trump Always Chickens Out.”  The suggestion is that his strongest threats – and some of investors’ worst resulting fears – won’t be realized.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given the long skein of good years in the markets, it seems today’s investors are motivated more by FOMO than by concern about the chance the market is high and likely to produce poor returns or even losses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, of course, the consensus of investors responsible for today’s asset prices probably view the fundamental outlook as more positive than I do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s the bottom line of the calculus?  Fundamentals appear to me to be less good overall than they were seven months ago, but at the same time, asset prices are high relative to earnings, higher than they were at the end of 2024, and at high valuations relative to history.  &lt;/strong&gt;Most bull markets are built through the addition of a “constellation of positives” on top of a well-functioning economy.  Today I see elements that include the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the positive psychology and “wealth effect” resulting from recent gains in markets, high-end real estate, and crypto,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the belief that, for most investors, there really is no alternative to the U.S. markets, and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the excitement surrounding today’s new, new thing: AI. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are the kinds of things that have the ability to fire investor imaginations and contribute to bull markets, and they certainly seem to be doing so now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;*            *            *&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I came across a great quote last year from John Stuart Mill (1859): &lt;strong&gt;“He who knows only his own side of the case knows little of that.”&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, if you’re not conversant with the arguments of those who oppose your position, you really can’t assess its validity.  Thus, I can’t responsibly advance my view without giving the other side of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In every strongly rising market, there has to be a justification for the extended valuations: the “bull case.”  If it didn’t exist, asset prices couldn’t be where they are.  &lt;/strong&gt;It’s usually some variation on “it’s different this time.”  Here’s how it goes today:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A p/e ratio is basically the result of applying a discounted cash flow calculation to a stream of earnings, as described above.  The main inputs for performing such a calculation and assigning a valuation are assumptions regarding the earnings’ growth rate, durability, and return on invested capital.  Compared to the past, today’s S&amp;P 500 is increasingly made up of companies that (a) grow faster, (b) are less cyclical, (c) require less incremental capital to grow, enabling them to generate more free cash flow, and (d) have much stronger competitive positions or “moats.”  Thus, they deserve above average p/e ratios.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This explanation makes complete sense.  It cites factors that really might be different.  And per Sir John Templeton, the first person that I know talked about the trap of “it’s different this time,” 20 percent of the time things really are; today I’d bet it’s more than 20 percent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, on one hand, “it’s different this time” is a recurring bull-market cliche that always bears scrutiny and on the other hand, failing to recognize when things actually are different is something that stands between the average investor and superiority.  &lt;/strong&gt;I just have no idea which of those two concerns is more valid today.  But investors should bear three things in mind:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the enormous likelihood that AI and related developments will change the world, &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the possibility that it is “different” for &lt;strong&gt;some&lt;/strong&gt; companies – those that truly embody the factors listed above and will demonstrate the “persistence” I described in &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/on-bubble-watch" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Bubble Watch&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but also&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the fact that in most “new, new things,” investors tend to treat far too many companies – and often the wrong ones – as likely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;*            *            *&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The existence of overvaluation can never be proved&lt;/strong&gt;, and there’s no reason to think the conditions discussed above imply there’ll be a correction anytime soon.  But, taken together, they tell me the stock market has moved from “elevated” to “worrisome.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What should you do about it?  I consider tactical actions in terms of the spectrum that runs from aggressiveness to defensiveness, and when valuations are high, I consider becoming more defensive.  In the “action shows” my wife, Nancy, and I like to watch, the Pentagon sometimes announces a Defense Readiness Condition, starting at DEFCON 5 and escalating as the danger grows to DEFCON 1, which indicates a nuclear attack is underway or imminent.  In a similar vein, I think of progressively applying the following Investment Readiness Conditions, or INVESTCONs, in the face of above average market valuations and optimistic investor behavior:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;6. Stop buying&lt;br /&gt;5. Reduce aggressive holdings and increase defensive holdings&lt;br /&gt;4. Sell off the remaining aggressive holdings&lt;br /&gt;3. Trim defensive holdings as well&lt;br /&gt;2. Eliminate all holdings&lt;br /&gt;1. Go short
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my view, it’s essentially impossible to reasonably reach the degree of certainty needed to implement INVESTCON 3, 2, or 1.  Because “overvaluation” is never synonymous with “sure to go down soon,” it’s rarely wise to go to those extremes.  I know I never have.  &lt;strong&gt;But I have no problem thinking it’s time for INVESTCON 5.&lt;/strong&gt; And if you lighten up on things that appear historically expensive and switch into things that appear safer, there may be relatively little to lose from the market continuing to grind higher for a while . . . or anyway not enough to lose sleep over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hasten to note, of course, that credit investments are generally more secure than stocks, and thus well suited to serve as defensive holdings in the climate I describe.  &lt;strong&gt;The narrow yield spreads mean today’s prospective returns on credit aren’t generous relative to those on “risk-free” assets in the context of history&lt;/strong&gt; (see &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/gimme-credit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gimme Credit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the details).  &lt;strong&gt;But the returns are significant in absolute terms, competitive with the historical returns on equities, and supported by the issuers’ contractual promise to pay interest and return principal, something that can’t be said for stocks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;August 13, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal Information and Disclosures&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum expresses the views of the author as of the date indicated and such views are subject to change without notice.  Oaktree has no duty or obligation to update the information contained herein.  Further, Oaktree makes no representation, and it should not be assumed, that past investment performance is an indication of future results.  Moreover, wherever there is the potential for profit there is also the possibility of loss.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum is being made available for educational purposes only and should not be used for any other purpose.  The information contained herein does not constitute and should not be construed as an offering of advisory services or an offer to sell or solicitation to buy any securities or related financial instruments in any jurisdiction.  Certain information contained herein concerning economic trends and performance is based on or derived from information provided by independent third-party sources.  Oaktree Capital Management, L.P. (“Oaktree”) believes that the sources from which such information has been obtained are reliable; however, it cannot guarantee the accuracy of such information and has not independently verified the accuracy or completeness of such information or the assumptions on which such information is based.  &lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum, including the information contained herein, may not be copied, reproduced, republished, or posted in whole or in part, in any form without the prior written consent of Oaktree.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;© 2025 Oaktree Capital Management, L.P.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
						
						
							
								

Share
 &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value&amp;text=Oaktree Capital: The Calculus of Value:%20https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/shareArticle?mini=true&amp;url=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value/%2F&amp;title=Oaktree Capital: The Calculus of Value&amp;summary=&amp;source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value/%2F&amp;quote=Oaktree Capital: The Calculus of Value" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:?subject=Oaktree Capital: The Calculus of Value&amp;body=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-calculus-of-value" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
								
							

						
					
				
			
		
	













	
		
			
				
					
						&lt;h2&gt;Related Content&lt;/h2&gt;
					
					
						
							
									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/gimme-credit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/the-memo-from-howard-marksd198ddb3-6ceb-4922-8cac-9ddfca1ae261.png?sfvrsn=7bfc7366_1" alt="Gimme Credit for article" /&gt;memosMar 6, 2025Gimme CreditRead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/on-bubble-watch" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/hm-memos_written-image-1_530x299px.png?sfvrsn=50697366_3" alt="On Bubble Watch for article" /&gt;memosJan 7, 2025On Bubble WatchRead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2000-01-02-bubble.pdf?sfvrsn=37bc0f65_5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/the-memo-from-howard-marksd198ddb3-6ceb-4922-8cac-9ddfca1ae261.png?sfvrsn=7bfc7366_1" alt="bubble.com for article" /&gt;memosJan 2, 2000bubble.comRead&lt;/a&gt;


								
								
									
										
											Load More
										
									
								
							
						
					

				
			

		

	
	
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="javascript:openPDF('The Calculus of Value_JPN','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/translated-memos/the-calculus-of-value_jpn.pdf?sfvrsn=a1a32966_1')" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Download PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</content:encoded>
      <enclosure url="javascript:openPDF('The Calculus of Value_JPN','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/translated-memos/the-calculus-of-value_jpn.pdf?sfvrsn=a1a32966_1')" type="application/pdf"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More on Repealing the Laws of Economics</title>
      <link>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics</link>
      <guid>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics</guid>
      <pubDate>Invalid Date</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[Last September, I wrote a memo titled Shall We Repeal the Laws of Economics? in which I described economies as organic entities that operate on their own pursuant to some underlying laws.  The best known is the law of supply and demand: ...]]&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded>&lt;![CDATA[ 





	
		
			
				PDF Translations
				
			
			
				&lt;ul&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Japanese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Korean
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Simplified Chinese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Traditional Chinese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
			
		
	



	
		
			
				
					
						
							
								
									
										
											Memos from Howard Marks
											Jun 18, 2025
										
									
									
										
											
											
											
										
									
								
								

									&lt;ul&gt;
											&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;PDF (English)&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;
																					&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a href="#" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;PDF (Translations)&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;

											&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo-podcast/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Listen to Memo&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;
																				&lt;li&gt;
											&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memos" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Archived Memos&lt;/a&gt;
										&lt;/li&gt;

									&lt;/ul&gt;

									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/email-alerts" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt;
								
							
						
						
							More on Repealing the Laws of Economics
							&lt;br /&gt;
							&lt;br /&gt;
							
							
							&lt;p&gt;Last September, I wrote a memo titled &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/shall-we-repeal-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shall We Repeal the Laws of Economics?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in which I described economies as organic entities that operate on their own pursuant to some underlying laws.  The best known is the law of supply and demand: in general, people will buy more of something as the price goes down and produce more of it as the price goes up.  Another has to do with incentives: in general, people will allocate resources (such as their labor) to the activities for which they will be best rewarded.  These and the rest of the rules are straightforward, and it doesn’t take a Ph.D. to understand them.  In fact, they’re part of human nature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;But governments sometimes want outcomes different than those a free-functioning economy will produce.  To that end, they enact rules and regulations designed to override the laws of economics.  Some governments even go so far as to adopt socialism or communism, creating economies where government commands take over entirely from the laws of economics.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rent Control&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A prime example discussed in my September memo was rent control.  When demand for apartments exceeds supply, it’s only natural that rents will rise, perhaps eventually to the point where people who live in a given location can’t afford to continue doing so.  But elected officials typically want to preserve neighborhoods.  They want their constituents to be able to continue renting apartments in their districts and not lose out to others who can pay more.  To deliver on this aspect of constituent service, they pass laws to limit rent increases.  Now people who otherwise couldn’t afford to live in the jurisdiction can do so.  Those tenants are happy, and that makes the elected officials happy, as happy constituents tend to vote for incumbents. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;But not everyone is happy.  Landlords are unhappy about not being able to charge the full rent they could charge in a free market, so they stop investing in their apartments and sometimes take them off the market.  Developers who might be interested in building new apartments refrain from doing so out of concern that they won’t be able to earn a sufficient return.  Also unhappy are people who would like to live in that location and can afford to pay market rents but are unable to find vacant apartments because they’re occupied by people paying below-market rents. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are at least two things wrong with this situation. &lt;strong&gt;The first is that governments are choosing winners and losers, rather than letting market forces do so.  &lt;/strong&gt;In the case of rent control, the people who occupy apartments (and potentially political incumbents) are the winners, but landlords, developers, and people looking for apartments are the losers.  The elected officials enacting rent control will say they’re only trying to produce fairness for existing occupants, but they’re obviously treating others unfairly.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In addition, there are negative implications for society overall.  &lt;/strong&gt;Tenants living in rent-controlled apartments enjoy a very valuable asset: a bargain-priced place to live.  But there’s no way to monetize that asset; they can only enjoy the benefit by continuing to live there.  For this reason, they tend not to move, reducing mobility for themselves and everyone else.  Rent control also discourages the upgrading of existing apartments and the construction of new apartments, so the housing stock fails to keep up with the needs of the community in terms of both condition and quantity.  In other words,&lt;strong&gt; governments can limit the rents landlords can charge for their apartments, but they can’t make developers build new ones.  &lt;/strong&gt;These things can reduce overall societal welfare and interfere with the movement of resources to the use where they’re most productive.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fire Insurance in California&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most unfortunately, earlier this year, in the aftermath of the Southern California wildfires, we witnessed an extreme economic consequence of overriding the laws of economics.  When fires decimated the communities of Pacific Palisades and Altadena, thousands lost their homes, including a dozen Oaktree employees.  On top of the severe disruption of all aspects of their lives, many of them are suffering extremely negative financial consequences.  This is because many were uninsured or underinsured, often as a result of actions taken by California insurance regulators.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of California’s government is firmly under the control of the Democratic party, which generally leans toward a high level of activism in general and intervention in economic matters in particular.  Notably, because the Democrats hold a super-majority in the state legislature and have little fear of potential Republican opponents, Democratic elected officials don’t have to moderate their behavior to pass legislation or hold on to their seats.  And just like the support for rent control – there’s a lot of that in California, too – the government sought to help out homeowners by limiting the premiums companies could charge for fire insurance.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In a sign of the times, I’ll let my new (and AI-powered) editorial assistant, Perplexity, fill you in on the background.  &lt;/strong&gt;I’ve simplified the format and added emphasis, but I haven’t changed a word.  What follows below is pretty close to what I would have produced in an hour or two:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the devastating fires of 2025, California’s fire insurance market was already in a state of crisis, shaped by a combination of regulatory constraints, insurer withdrawals, and mounting wildfire risk.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Insurers were prohibited from using forward-looking catastrophe models to set rates for wildfire risk.  Instead, they were required by law to base their rates on historical average losses over the previous 20 years.  This approach became increasingly problematic as wildfires grew more frequent and severe, making historical data a poor predictor of future risk.  Regulations also prevented insurers from raising premiums to reflect increased reinsurance costs, further limiting their ability to price policies according to actual risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major insurers began withdrawing from the California market or ceasing to write new policies in fire-prone areas.  Chubb stopped writing new policies for high-value homes in 2021, Allstate followed in 2022, and State Farm, the state’s largest home insurer, stopped writing new policies in 2023.  In 2024, State Farm announced non-renewals for over 70,000 policies statewide, including thousands in high-risk areas like Pacific Palisades and Altadena, just months before the 2025 fires.  Other insurers, including Tokio Marine America and its subsidiaries, also exited the market in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homeowners who managed to keep their policies often faced dramatic premium hikes. For example, some saw their annual premiums rise from $4,500 to $18,000.  As a result, many property owners either lost coverage or could not afford to insure their properties, leading to widespread underinsurance.  &lt;strong&gt;By the time of the 2025 fires, fewer than a quarter of affected properties were insured against fire.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The state-backed FAIR Plan, intended as a last-resort insurance option, saw a surge in enrollment as private insurers withdrew.  However, FAIR Plan coverage is limited and more expensive than private insurance, often requiring supplemental policies to achieve adequate protection.  The FAIR Plan’s exposure to wildfire risk increased dramatically, raising concerns about its solvency in the event of another catastrophic fire season.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;California law provided for a mandatory one-year moratorium on non-renewals and cancellations of residential insurance policies in areas affected by a declared state of emergency.  This protection applied after major wildfires but did not prevent insurers from withdrawing or refusing to renew policies before such emergencies were declared.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The regulatory approval process for rate changes became increasingly slow, with the average time for approval rising from 157 days (2013–2019) to 293 days (2020–2022). This lag contributed to insurer frustration and market instability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Perplexity notes, insurers were told they couldn’t price fire policies to reflect increases in the frequency and severity of forest fires.  Likewise, they couldn’t raise prices to pass through the higher premiums their reinsurers were charging based on the increased frequency and severity.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a $5 million house has a 1% probability of burning down in a given year and the insurance regulator says you can only charge $25,000 per year for a fire policy, what will you do?  (Note: I didn’t need Perplexity to tell me the insurance company faces an expected payout of $50,000 on that policy: 1% of $5 million.)  The answer’s simple: you don’t write that policy. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lesson here is the same as with rent control but rendered much more graphic by the catastrophic fires.  &lt;strong&gt;Just as with rents, you can limit the price insurers can charge for coverage, but you can’t make them provide coverage at that price.  &lt;/strong&gt;In this case, governmental efforts to enforce a non-free-market solution deprived many of access to insurance, ultimately bringing misery to thousands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anything Else?  Oh Yes: What About Tariffs?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s 2½ pages of prologue leading up to my main topic: tariffs.  As we’ve had two months since “Liberation Day” on April 2 to think about them, I’m going to attempt a complete discussion (and also try to stay objective and apolitical).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, what is a tariff?  According to Merriam-Webster, it’s “a schedule of duties imposed by a government on imported or in some countries exported goods.”  In other words, it’s a tax.  The exporting company, the exporting country, or the importing company might choose to pay some or all of the tariff, but only if they’re willing to spend money to maintain their market share in the importing country.  Otherwise, the tariff will be paid by the end-consumer in the form of a price increase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is the U.S. raising tariffs?  The reason for President Trump’s pro-tariff stance is no doubt his long-held conviction that our negative trade balance in goods (the amount by which our imports exceed our exports – $1.2 trillion in 2024) is proof that foreign countries are ripping us off.  As he puts it, “we’re losing $5 billion dollars a day on trade.”  I’ll leave aside my insistence that international trade isn’t a rip-off in itself – it’s literally a fair trade since the exporting country gets the money, and the importing country gets the goods it desires.  I’ll also overlook the U.S.’s $290 billion positive trade balance in 2024 in services – things advanced countries would tend to sell, such as financial, communication, and information services, along with intellectual property.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are tariffs meant to achieve?  On April 9, in my memo &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nobody Knows (Yet Again)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I guessed at President Trump’s goals in enacting them as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;support U.S. manufacturing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;discourage imports&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;encourage exports&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;shrink or eliminate our trade deficit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;make supply chains more secure through onshoring&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;deter unfair trade practices aimed at the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;force other countries to the negotiating table&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;generate revenue for the U.S. Treasury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I also wrote, every one of these eight goals is desirable in itself and something tariffs should bring about.  Essentially, raising the cost of imported goods – and that’s what tariffs do – should be a step in all these directions.  The important question in economics is what other effects there might be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me digress a minute for a primer on trade.  Assume there are two countries with a wall between them.  In Country A, workers make $100 an hour and a car costs $50,000.  In Country B, workers make $50 an hour and the same car costs $35,000.  Because there’s no cross-border trade, all remains well and good.  But if the wall comes down, some enterprising businessperson will ship cars from Country B to Country A, where they’ll sell like hotcakes at a price of $36,000 (adding in $1,000 for transportation).  &lt;strong&gt;Highly unequal wages and prices – examples of what economists call disequilibria – can’t persist if things like labor and goods are mobile.  That’s trade at work.  &lt;/strong&gt;Thus, over time, workers will move from Country B to Country A for the higher wages.  That will cause wages in Country A to come down (more workers available) and wages in Country B to go up (fewer workers available) and, eventually, Country B’s cars to no longer be cheaper.  &lt;strong&gt;Tariffs are like the wall posited above.  They impede foreign competition, enabling domestic manufacturers to sell their products even if they represent an inferior bargain.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we accomplish the first two goals listed above, both of which are among the foreseeable results of what’s called “protectionism,” because tariffs protect domestic industries from encroachment from abroad.  If imports are rendered more expensive by tariffs – or if they’re banned altogether by trade barriers – domestic manufacturers face reduced competition from imports.  That’s good for domestic manufacturers and their workers, but what else happens?  First, prices might rise; there are already reports of domestic manufacturers raising prices under the umbrella of higher import prices.  Second, they may begin producing inferior goods because they don’t have to compete against imports.  Third, because they don’t have to worry about competition from low-paid workers in foreign countries, domestic workers are able to form strong labor unions and demand high wages, further adding to the cost of domestic goods.  &lt;strong&gt;Thus, consumers pay more than they would if imports were unconstrained, and the volume of exports may actually decline, since domestic producers might become globally uncompetitive.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is the U.S. Right to Raise Tariffs?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I was a boy, the phrase “foreign car” was practically an oxymoron.  The first two Volkswagens came to America in 1949.  They were among roughly 7,500 cars imported that year, representing only 0.03% – that’s three one-hundredths of a percent – of all cars sold in the U.S.  But in 2024, according to a fact sheet published by the White House in March, half the 16 million vehicles sold in the U.S. were imports, and they included 500,000 Volkswagens (usimportdata.com).  Why?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There were a number of reasons for the success of the foreign manufacturers, including quality, engineering and marketing, but one main reason was that consumers concluded that cars made in the U.S. were more expensive than foreign cars but not correspondingly better.  &lt;/strong&gt;(My first car, an Oldsmobile Cutlass, cost $3,200 in 1965, and a Volkswagen Beetle cost just half as much.)  U.S. auto workers were able to command higher wages than those paid in Germany or Japan, plus a unique fringe benefit package including lifetime medical care, which was said in 2008 to amount to $1,900 per car.  This represented a tremendous competitive burden.  Sales of cars made in the U.S. were brisk until the rise of international trade brought imports to our shores, at which point the imports imposed economic reality upon the Big Three U.S. auto makers, with their higher cost structures and dated products.  (It must be noted that Volkswagen’s success in penetrating the U.S. market is said to have been aided by subsidies from the German government.)  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The result was lost sales for domestic producers and the movement of production overseas.  Could this have been avoided?  Only if U.S. workers were willing to work at wages comparable to those paid to workers in other countries.  Otherwise, the movement of jobs to foreign countries was probably inevitable.  U.S. automakers could have responded to the new foreign competition by improving quality or boosting productivity, but it’s unlikely they would be able to offset their higher cost structures in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Niall Ferguson, the British economic historian, did an excellent podcast on April 10, just after the new tariffs were introduced.  In it, he said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every single economy that industrialized, from the late 18th century through the 19th century into the 20th century, reached a peak at some point along the way, roughly when the per capita GDP reached $40,000 [presumably in today’s dollars], after which manufacturing as a share of employment declined.  And the decline is essentially identical for all developed economies, as people move out of working in factories and move into service-sector jobs, which are less physically demanding and require more education.  So that happened everywhere.  It wasn’t just in the United States. . . .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, progress takes countries up the curve from subsistence to prosperity, and along the way they transition from agriculture- to manufacturing- to service-based economics.  The success of the U.S. economy caused many of its workers to leave the manufacturing sector.  As a result, only 8% of our non-farm jobs are in manufacturing today, down from about 30% in 1950.  According to Ferguson’s research, that probably didn’t have much to do with the automobile industry in particular or with unfair trade practices applied by other nations.  And it’s probably not because people couldn’t find jobs in manufacturing: according to the Bureau of Labor Statistics, there are about 400,000 job openings today in U.S. manufacturing, and no one’s rushing to fill them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It stands to reason that a country cannot pull ahead of others in terms of per capita income and standard of living and expect to continue as mainly a manufacturing economy.  And neither can we return to being one.  Here’s more from Niall Ferguson:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We cannot go back to the 1950s, or for that matter to the 1910s, not socially, and not economically.  There is not a world in which these policies could lead to the reindustrialization of the United States, because it is way more expensive to do manufacturing in this country than it is to do it practically anywhere else . . .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It can be appropriate for a government to decide that certain goods should be made domestically and certain industries should be protected.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The obvious example is when national security is at stake.  We might conclude that our military shouldn’t buy defense materiel abroad, since we don’t want to be dependent on foreign suppliers, especially those in countries that could be antagonists.  If you need further persuasion, Joe Nocera wrote this in a May 6 article in &lt;em&gt;The Free Press&lt;/em&gt; titled “The Intellectual Godfathers of Protectionism”:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there was any doubt that America had put its security at risk in allowing the Chinese to take over so much manufacturing, COVID put it to rest.  A closer look showed that the US needed China to build its ships, to gain access to rare-earth minerals, to export its semiconductors and literally thousands of other necessary products. . .  .  [Quoting Rana Foroohar], “People finally woke up to the fact that 80 percent of our supply chain had been outsourced to our biggest strategic rival.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A tariff also might reasonably be enacted to protect an iconic industry that’s important to national identity.  The Swiss might want to bar imports of white cheese with holes in it, just as the French might prohibit importation of white wine with bubbles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lastly, tariffs might well be applied against countries that employ unfair trade practices, such as subsidizing their domestic producers and denying foreign companies access to their markets.  Tariff hawks assert that other countries have been doing things like this for years, leading to our massive trade deficit.    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Governments can opt to levy tariffs in cases like these, even if they interfere with the operation of the free market.  The argument we heard before the so-called Liberation Day was for “targeted tariffs” that would be applied selectively to accomplish these goals.  But that’s different from taxing all goods from all countries.  Governments can’t require everything to be made at home without consequences.  Indeed, given that the U.S. is bigger and richer than most other countries, isn’t it inescapable that we’ll buy more from other countries than they’ll buy from us?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tariffs are, primarily, an effort to cause goods to be made domestically even when equivalent foreign goods are cheaper or better (or both).  Governments can make that happen by erecting barriers that keep foreign goods out or make them more expensive.  That protects domestic industries and domestic workers, but at the expense of domestic consumers (and global welfare).  &lt;strong&gt;That’s a tradeoff – the kind of thing free markets require and leaders who would mandate economic outcomes would prefer to ignore.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Any Other Laws We Can Dispense With?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll now leave the subject of repealing the laws of economics to comment briefly on our elected officials’ willingness to ignore them.  I’ll discuss two examples. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first relates to fiscal discipline.  In short, the U.S. government habitually spends more than it takes in, and I think this is one of the very worst things going on in our country.  As I mentioned in &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nobody Knows (Yet Again)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the U.S. is able to do this because to date the world has given it virtually unlimited credit at particularly low interest rates.  The result has been fiscal deficits in 41 of the last 45 years and trillion-dollar-plus deficits in all of the last five.  If your brother-in-law behaved this way, you’d call him irresponsible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Economist John Maynard Keynes said in the 1930s that if an economy is growing too slowly to produce the needed jobs, the government should engage in deficit spending.  By doing so – putting more into the economy through spending than it takes out in taxes – it stimulates economic growth and thus job creation.  And then, when prosperity is restored, the government should run a surplus – spending less than it takes in – and pay down the debt.  Today, U.S. politicians from both parties are in the habit of spending without regard to the deficit, and the part about surpluses and paydowns has been forgotten.  In fiscal year 2024, for example, &lt;strong&gt;the U.S. ran a deficit of roughly $1.8 trillion, or 6.4% of GDP, in a time of prosperity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we continue to borrow and add to the national debt every year at a rate that exceeds the growth of GDP, the interest bill at a constant interest rate will take up a bigger and bigger percentage of the budget, adding to future deficits and debt.  The interest bill will compound as a percentage of GDP, and so will the debt.  We already spend more on interest each year than on defense.  And the interest bill will soar further if rates rise in the future – whether in response to inflation or deterioration of the U.S.’s creditworthiness – and maturing low-rate debt has to be replaced in a higher-rate environment.  How long can we increase debt faster than GDP? &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;No one can say when, but it makes sense to assume we’ll eventually reach a point at which our credit is no longer unlimited and our interest rates are no longer so low.  As Warren Buffett said at the May 3 Berkshire Hathaway annual meeting: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re operating at a fiscal deficit now that is unsustainable over a very long period of time.  We don’t know whether that means two years or 20 years, because there’s never been a country like the United States.  But you know, this is something that can’t go on forever . . . and it has the aspect to it that it gets uncontrollable at a certain point. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fixing this won’t be easy, as Buffett went on to say, because we’ve developed bad spending habits and leaders have pandered to voters by keeping taxes low.  There are only two possible parts to the solution: curtail spending and/or expand revenues.  No one wants to be taxed higher, and no one wants to see the programs they benefit from reduced.  &lt;strong&gt;Because what’s required is austerity, all aspects of which are unpleasant, few people in Washington genuinely pursue a solution.  &lt;/strong&gt;President Trump tried to cut “waste, fraud and abuse” through Elon Musk and his Department of Government Efficiency, but the potential savings went from $2 trillion to $1 trillion and ended up in the low hundreds of billions of dollars at most, which is a relatively immaterial amount.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the House of Representatives has passed a bill that would extend tax cuts that were enacted in 2017 and supposed to end this year.  Extending them would significantly increase the deficit relative to what it would be if the cuts were permitted to expire as scheduled.  In addition, the bill includes some quirky revenue reducers, such as exempting overtime pay and tips from taxation and increasing the standard deduction for senior citizens.  The non-partisan Congressional Budget Office estimates the bill will add an aggregate $2.4 trillion to the deficit over the next 10 years.  How could the House have passed a bill in May 2025 that neither raised taxes nor cut spending?  The rejoinder, as usual, is that the bill – and especially the tax cuts – will stimulate the economy, causing the deficits and the debt to shrink as a percentage of GDP.  I think it’s fair to say this tactic hasn’t worked to date.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re simply not tackling our deficits.  We’re not implementing meaningful spending cuts or tax increases.  &lt;strong&gt;The idea that spending shouldn’t exceed revenues is completely out the window.  George F. Will listed nine tenets of progressivism in a May 28 article in &lt;em&gt;The Washington Post&lt;/em&gt;, and one was as follows: “limitless borrowing from future Americans to fund today’s Americans’ consumption of government goods and services.” &lt;/strong&gt; I think that absolutely nails the thinking that guides all of Washington, with the exception of the rare true fiscal conservative. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same is true with regard to the funding of Social Security.  Our Social Security program was designed as a pay-as-you-go program, not a funded endowment that spins off benefit payments like a pension fund.  Your tax payments are used to pay benefits to people who are retired, and in the same way, your benefits in retirement will come out of taxes paid by those working at that time.  In the past, when many people were working relative to the number who had retired, tax receipts exceeded benefit payments, and the surplus accumulated in the Social Security Trust Funds.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, the problem is that the number of workers paying into Social Security has fallen relative to the number of retirees taking out.  In addition, retirees are living longer, but workers aren’t paying taxes longer.  Thus, tax revenues coming in have fallen relative to benefit payments going out, and they are insufficient to pay benefits.  The difference is made up by drawing from the Trust Funds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The math is simple: there are x dollars in the Trust Funds, and they earn interest at Treasury rates.  By projecting growth in the number of workers and retirees, benefit payments and life expectancies, you can estimate with some confidence the year when, in the absence of corrective action, the Trust Funds will be exhausted.  That year is 2035.  At that point, either (a) benefit payments will have to be cut so that they equal tax receipts (and it’s estimated that receipts will be sufficient to pay only 79% of the promised benefits) or (b) the shortfall will have to be paid from the general U.S. government budget, further adding to the deficit.  &lt;strong&gt;Nothing in this paragraph is conjecture.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are many options for solving this problem.  They include the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;raise the Social Security tax rate
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;increase the amount of earnings on which Social Security tax is paid (the current cap is $176,100)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;raise the retirement age&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;shrink retirement benefits&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;reduce the cost-of-living adjustment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;apply a means-based test, phasing out benefits as a retiree’s income rises&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is that all the above would be wildly unpopular with voters.  It’s assumedly for that reason that the two political parties have one thing they agree on: “hands off Social Security.”  Thus, it hasn’t been dealt with in over a decade.  What would happen to executives in your organization who turned a blind eye to such a foreseeable problem?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The members of the Baby Boomer generation to which I belong – people born between 1946 and 1964 – are unusually numerous, disproportionately affluent and probably above average in tendency to vote.  Thus, they have significant political influence, having cast 38% of the votes in the 2020 presidential election.  All the Boomers are in or near retirement, and no politician wants to antagonize them.  Thus, elected officials can’t stand the political heat associated with fixing Social Security, so they punt.  As a result, the insolvency of the Social Security Trust Funds is sure to occur only ten years or so from now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s get personal.  I started getting Social Security when I turned 70, the latest possible opportunity, and I now receive $4,612 per month.  &lt;strong&gt;That’s ridiculous: I and other wealthy Boomers shouldn’t get Social Security benefits.  &lt;/strong&gt;As with the national debt, the problems associated with Social Security will be left for our descendants to deal with.  &lt;strong&gt;This is a matter of serious generational equity that deserves attention but doesn’t receive it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our elected officials may believe the status quo can be maintained forever, or more likely they count on being out of office by the time the wheels come off.  But certainly, they’re not facing up to reality.  The behavior in Washington with regard to both the fiscal deficit and the precariousness of Social Security remind me of the tale of the guy who jumped off the 20-story building.  As he passed the 10th floor, he said, “So far, so good.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;*            *            *&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When allowed to function, the laws of economics provide incentives that encourage innovation, productivity and efficiency, creating prosperity and optimizing overall welfare.  &lt;/strong&gt;For example, globalization delivers the benefits of “comparative advantage,” under which each country produces the things it can make better and cheaper and, as a result, consumers everywhere enjoy the best possible combination of quality and price.  In the process, workers in the producing nations receive the highest possible pay for their labor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;And when insurance companies are permitted to pursue business and price policies as they choose, 
market competition will yield the best possible solution in terms of coverage that’s available and fairly priced.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Of course, optimizing overall welfare is different from ensuring that all individuals prosper.  &lt;/strong&gt;Workers in a country that lacks comparative advantage may lose their jobs or see their wages decline if not protected by tariffs and trade barriers.  And buyers of insurance may pay more for coverage than they would if insurance commissioners limited premiums.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The only way to strive for universal prosperity and “fairness” – no winners and losers – is for government to mandate it.  But the efforts to do so have never been successful&lt;/strong&gt;, as described above and in &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/shall-we-repeal-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shall We Repeal the Laws of Economics?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It didn’t work for the Soviet Union, and it didn’t work in shielding homeowners from the economic impact of the California wildfires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The much better way is for governments to allow markets to operate freely and deal with undesirable side effects.  Examples include making sure a safety net gives workers who lose their jobs income support and retraining, as well as making sure companies and countries don’t engage in improper, anti-competitive practices.  Choosing to limit effects in this way may involve tradeoffs, with costs that a society can reasonably decide to bear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The bottom line on all the above is that free-market economies don’t produce perfect solutions, but efforts to significantly control them make things much worse.  There can be no solution that gives everyone what they want.  All things considered, however, the laws of economics lead to the best solutions that can be attained.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;June 18, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal Information and Disclosures&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum expresses the views of the author as of the date indicated and such views are subject to change without notice. Oaktree has no duty or obligation to update the information contained herein. Further, Oaktree makes no representation, and it should not be assumed, that past investment performance is an indication of future results. Moreover, wherever there is the potential for profit there is also the possibility of loss.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum is being made available for educational purposes only and should not be used for any other purpose. The information contained herein does not constitute and should not be construed as an offering of advisory services or an offer to sell or solicitation to buy any securities or related financial instruments in any jurisdiction. Certain information contained herein concerning economic trends and performance is based on or derived from information provided by independent third-party sources. Oaktree Capital Management, L.P. (“Oaktree”) believes that the sources from which such information has been obtained are reliable; however, it cannot guarantee the accuracy of such information and has not independently verified the accuracy or completeness of such information or the assumptions on which such information is based. &lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum, including the information contained herein, may not be copied, reproduced, republished, or posted in whole or in part, in any form without the prior written consent of Oaktree.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;© 2025 Oaktree Capital Management, L.P.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
						
						
							
								

Share
 &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics&amp;text=Oaktree Capital: More on Repealing the Laws of Economics:%20https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/shareArticle?mini=true&amp;url=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics/%2F&amp;title=Oaktree Capital: More on Repealing the Laws of Economics&amp;summary=&amp;source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics/%2F&amp;quote=Oaktree Capital: More on Repealing the Laws of Economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:?subject=Oaktree Capital: More on Repealing the Laws of Economics&amp;body=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
								
							

						
					
				
			
		
	













	
		
			
				
					
						&lt;h2&gt;Related Content&lt;/h2&gt;
					
					
						
							
									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo-podcast/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/hm_memo_podcast.png?sfvrsn=61247366_3" alt="More on Repealing the Laws of Economics for audio" /&gt;memosJun 18, 2025More on Repealing the Laws of EconomicsListen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/hm-memos_written-image-2_530x299px.png?sfvrsn=4f697366_10" alt="Nobody Knows (Yet Again) for article" /&gt;memosApr 9, 2025Nobody Knows (Yet Again)Read&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/shall-we-repeal-the-laws-of-economics" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/the-memo-from-howard-marksd198ddb3-6ceb-4922-8cac-9ddfca1ae261.png?sfvrsn=7bfc7366_1" alt="Shall We Repeal the Laws of Economics? for article" /&gt;memosSep 19, 2024Shall We Repeal the Laws of Economics?Read&lt;/a&gt;


								
								
									
										
											Load More
										
									
								
							
						
					

				
			

		

	
	
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="javascript:openPDF('More on Repealing the Laws of Economics_JPN','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/translated-memos/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics_jpn.pdf?sfvrsn=a162a66_1')" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Download PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</content:encoded>
      <enclosure url="javascript:openPDF('More on Repealing the Laws of Economics_JPN','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/translated-memos/more-on-repealing-the-laws-of-economics_jpn.pdf?sfvrsn=a162a66_1')" type="application/pdf"/>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nobody Knows (Yet Again)</title>
      <link>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again</link>
      <guid>https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again</guid>
      <pubDate>Invalid Date</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;![CDATA[On Monday, September 15, 2008, shortly after the close of the New York Stock Exchange, Lehman Brothers surprised the world by filing for bankruptcy. This came on the heels of rescues/bankruptcies of Bear Stearns and Merrill Lynch and was...]]&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded>&lt;![CDATA[ 





	
		
			
				PDF Translations
				
			
			
				&lt;ul&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Japanese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Korean
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Simplified Chinese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;
							&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;
								Traditional Chinese
							&lt;/a&gt;
						&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
			
		
	



	
		
			
				
					
						
							
								
									
										
											Memos from Howard Marks
											Apr 9, 2025
										
									
									
										
											
											
											
										
									
								
								

									&lt;ul&gt;
											&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;PDF (English)&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;
																					&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a href="#" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;PDF (Translations)&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;

											&lt;li&gt;
												&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo-podcast/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Listen to Memo&lt;/a&gt;
											&lt;/li&gt;
																				&lt;li&gt;
											&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memos" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Archived Memos&lt;/a&gt;
										&lt;/li&gt;

									&lt;/ul&gt;

									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/email-alerts" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt;
								
							
						
						
							Nobody Knows (Yet Again)
							&lt;br /&gt;
							&lt;br /&gt;
							
							
							&lt;p&gt;On Monday, September 15, 2008, shortly after the close of the New York Stock Exchange, Lehman Brothers surprised the world by filing for bankruptcy. This came on the heels of rescues/bankruptcies of Bear Stearns and Merrill Lynch and was followed quite soon by more of the same at Wachovia, Washington Mutual, and AIG. Market participants quickly concluded that the U.S. financial sector was on the verge of melting down. It had become patently obvious (unlike a few days earlier) that financial institutions might fall like dominoes due to the combination of (a) financial deregulation, (b) a manic housing boom, (c) unwise mortgage lending, (d) the structuring of mortgages into thousands of tranched securities that were rated too high, (e) investment in these securities on the part of highly levered banks, and (f) “counterparty risk” resulting from the banks’ interconnectedness. Reflecting this fear, the markets embarked on what felt like a downward spiral without end. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thought I should comment on these developments and the outlook, and the result was a memo called &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/2008-09-19-nobody-knows.pdf?sfvrsn=cbbc0f65_6" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nobody Knows&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, published four days later. I affirmed my ignorance of the future as usual, but to an even greater degree given that all prior expectations had been upended. Nobody knew – especially me – whether the spiral could be arrested. Nevertheless, I concluded that we had to assume it would, and thus that we should plow money into financial assets at their highly discounted prices. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was nothing anyone could say they “knew,” and that included me. I was limited to gaming out my conclusions, which were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;we can’t confidently predict the end of the world,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;we’d have no idea what to do if we knew the world would end,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the things we’d do to gird for the end of the world would be disastrous if it didn’t end, and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;most of the time the world doesn’t end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clearly, I didn’t base these conclusions on knowledge of the future. But I saw no logical choice other than to start putting money to work, including the $10 billion that was sitting uninvested in Opportunities Fund VIIb. We had formed that fund to prepare for an elevated opportunity in distressed debt. How could we not follow through when one arrived, especially given the bargains — and the extraordinary yields — available on some of the highest quality debt we’d ever been able to buy in distress? &lt;strong&gt;And yet, we admittedly had no idea what the future would bring.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I can’t claim to have analyzed the future.&lt;/strong&gt; In fact, I consider the phrase “analyze the future” one of the great oxymorons. The future has not yet been created, and it’s subject to millions of complex, unquantifiable, and unknowable factors that will always be in flux. You can ponder the future and speculate about it, but there’s nothing to “analyze” and certainly there wasn’t in the early days of the Global Financial Crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In March 2020, I reused the title of the 2008 memo for &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/nobody-knows-ii.pdf?sfvrsn=108eb165_8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nobody Knows II&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, my first memo during the Covid-19 pandemic. In it, I cited Harvard epidemiologist Marc Lipsitch, who said we usually make decisions on the basis of (a) facts, (b) informed extrapolations from analogous experiences, and (c) opinion or speculation. But since there were no applicable facts regarding a Covid pandemic and no analogous experiences, we were left with only speculation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I want to say right here about 2008 and the other crises I’ve invested through – as well as today – that I don’t reach my conclusions with confidence or act without trepidation.&lt;/strong&gt; There’s absolutely no place for certainty in the world of investing, and that’s particularly true at turning points and during upheavals. I’m never sure my answers are right, but if I can reason out what’s most logical, I feel I have to move in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Uncertain Outlook&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my February memo &lt;em&gt;2024 in Review&lt;/em&gt;, which went only to clients, I said the word to describe the Trump administration was “uncertainty.” President Trump’s thinking seems less predictable than that of most presidents, largely because it doesn’t necessarily hew to a consistent ideology, and it’s very much subject to being applied and revised tactically. It should be noted, however, that Trump has complained about how the U.S. is treated in world trade and argued in support of tariffs since at least 1987. Having said that, and even though we knew he was going to hike tariffs, no one anticipated the magnitude of the increases. Clearly the markets hadn’t.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week’s events remind us of the events of 2008 and the Global Financial Crisis they produced. All norms have been overthrown. The way world trade has operated for the last 80 years may be of little relevance to the future. The impact on economies and the world at large is entirely unpredictable. We’re faced with large-scale decisions, yet again there are no facts or prior experiences on which to base those decisions. Truly nobody knows, and a lot of this memo will be about things we can’t know for sure. But I hope it’ll help you organize and evaluate the issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to point out that there are no experts on the subject at hand. Economists have analytical tools and theories to apply, but no economist and no tool will produce a conclusion in this instance that we can follow with confidence. There have been no large-scale trade wars in the modern era; thus, the theories are untested. Investors, businesspeople, academics, and government leaders will all give advice, but none of them is much more likely to be right than the average intelligent observer. The things on which everyone will agree are obvious, such as the likelihood of higher prices. The less obvious truths will be harder to discern.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the things I insist on is that even for someone who deals with the future via forecasts, a forecast isn’t enough. &lt;strong&gt;In addition to a forecast, you also need a good sense for the probability your forecast is correct, since not all forecasts are created equal. In this case, under these circumstances, it must be accepted that forecasts are even less likely to prove correct than usual. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why? Primarily because of the vast number of unprecedented unknowns involved in the current matter, which has the potential to turn into the biggest economic development in our lifetimes.&lt;/strong&gt; There’s no such thing as foreknowledge here, just complexity and uncertainty, and we must accept that as true. &lt;strong&gt;This means that if we insist on achieving certainty or even confidence as a precondition for action, we’ll be frozen into inaction. Or, I dare say, if we conclude we’ve reached decisions with certainty or confidence, we’ll probably be mistaken. We must make our decisions in the absence of those things.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But we also have to bear in mind that deciding not to act isn’t the opposite of acting; it’s an act in itself.&lt;/strong&gt; The decision to not act – to leave a portfolio unchanged – should be scrutinized as critically as a decision to make changes. The old saws that are the refuge of terrified investors – “we’re not going to try to catch a falling knife” and “we should wait for the dust to settle and the uncertainty to be resolved” – cannot in themselves be allowed to determine our behavior. &lt;strong&gt;I love the title of a book by a market analyst named Walter Deemer: “When the Time Comes to Buy, You Won’t Want To.”&lt;/strong&gt; The negative developments that make for the greatest price declines are terrifying, and they discourage buying. But, when unfavorable developments are raining down, that’s often the best time to step up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lastly, given Trump’s tactical focus, it’s important to bear in mind that absolutely everything is subject to change. It shouldn’t surprise anyone if he extracts concessions and declares victory . . . or if he responds to other countries’ retaliation by escalating further.&lt;/strong&gt; Thus, I told a Wharton conference on Friday that if anyone thinks they know what a given tariff rate will be three months from now, I’ll bet good money they’re wrong – even without knowing what they think the answer is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tariffs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are President Trump’s reasons for enacting his tariffs, and are they valid? On the day of the announcement, I heard a commentator on television credit Trump’s “impulses” as having some justification. What are his goals? They include some or all of the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;support U.S. manufacturing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;encourage exports&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;discourage imports&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;shrink or eliminate our trade deficit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;make supply chains more secure through onshoring&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;deter unfair trade practices aimed at the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;force other countries to the negotiating table&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;generate revenue for the U.S. Treasury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It must be acknowledged that every one of these things is desirable in itself and a logical result of tariffs. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If only it were that easy. &lt;strong&gt;The problem is that in the real world, and especially in economics, there are second- and third-order consequences that must be considered.&lt;/strong&gt; If there weren’t, economics would be dependable like the physical sciences, as in “if you do A, then B happens.” As theoretical physicist Richard Feynman said, “imagine how much harder physics would be if electrons had feelings.” Well, economies and markets are made up almost entirely of people, and people do have feelings, rendering reactions unpredictable. In economics, others will react to action A, as well as to result B that action A produces, and we have to think about the effect of those reactions. Not only are repercussions often significant, but they’re also unpredictable. Further, politics plays a particularly important and unpredictable role in the matter at hand, with a calculus all its own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are some of the likely consequences of Trump’s tariffs? The list is long, and many are particularly serious:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;retaliation by other countries&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;price increases and rising inflation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;destruction of demand due to price increases and declining consumer confidence&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;recession and lost jobs, both in the U.S. and around the world&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;supply shortages&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;a massive change in the world order&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are many threads to follow, and if I try to do them all justice, we’ll be here forever. I’ll just touch on a few.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some countries will negotiate – after all, in most cases, to borrow Trump’s terminology, the U.S. is “holding the best cards.” But others won’t, perhaps because their leaders will insist on looking strong, leading to escalation. Higher “reciprocal tariffs” are unlikely to accomplish anything positive on balance and will probably make life worse for both parties. It will be of scant satisfaction if the incremental problems we encounter are less bad than those befalling other nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is little doubt that the tariffs will raise prices. Tariffs are taxes on imports, and someone has to pay them. This is true in the case of goods brought in from abroad, as well as goods made in the U.S. that incorporate imported materials or components. This means the effect will be widespread. While it’s the importer who pays the tariff at the border, the cost is usually passed on to the ultimate purchaser of the goods, the consumer. In theory, the manufacturer, exporter, exporting country, or importer can choose to absorb the tax to preserve their business, but they won’t be eager to cut into their profits to do so, and in many cases their profit margins aren’t high enough to allow them to do so. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that in my March 2022 memo, &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-pendulum-in-international-affairs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Pendulum in International Affairs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I observed that between 1995 and 2020, U.S. consumer durable prices declined by 40% in real terms and total inflation averaged only 1.8% per year. Consumer durables consist mostly of vehicles, appliances, and electronics, and a big percentage of these have been imported. &lt;strong&gt;What would inflation have been if low-cost imports were discouraged or precluded?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;But let’s assume the first three goals listed above are actually achieved, causing more of the goods purchased in the U.S. to be made in the U.S.: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, in most cases, there isn’t sufficient manufacturing capacity that can be switched on. For example, I doubt there’s a factory in the U.S. capable of producing flat screens for TVs or computers. It would take years to build enough capacity to satisfy a meaningful percentage of U.S. demand, meaning in the interim there would be shortages and/or selling prices would likely be at the old levels plus the tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, the new factories designed to bring back manufacturing jobs would take years to permit and build, and the cost of construction would have to be justified by an expectation of profits many years out in the future. This adds further complexity to decisions that had already been made challenging by uncertainty regarding future developments in automation and AI. Are CEOs likely to commit to those investments based on tariffs that might be subject to renegotiation (or discontinuation when a new administration takes office)? Bear in mind that Trump’s 25% tariff on Mexican and Canadian goods replaced the United States-Mexico-Canada Agreement he negotiated during his first term and that went into effect in 2020, which in turn replaced NAFTA, which was enacted in 1994. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Third, there probably aren’t enough skilled workers available in the U.S. to take the place of all those in China and the developing world who presently make goods for us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fourth, why have Americans been buying imports in the first place? Because they’re cheaper.&lt;/strong&gt; Why did the U.S. lose the jobs it lost? Because American workers were paid more than workers elsewhere for the same job, but U.S. products weren’t good enough to justify higher selling prices. That’s why the U.S. went from importing 330 Volkswagens in 1950 to more than 400,000 in 2012. It wasn’t that U.S. tariffs were too low. The simple truth is that foreign goods often cost less than comparable goods made in the U.S. &lt;strong&gt;Even if tariffs are set high enough in the future to render U.S.-made goods cheaper than imports-cum-tariffs, the prices will be higher in the absolute than Americans are used to paying.&lt;/strong&gt; This morning, for example, it was mentioned on TV that a smartphone made in the U.S. might cost $3,500.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since most Americans have little income left over after paying for necessities, the result of higher prices is likely to be declining standards of living. That’s true unless wages rise as fast as prices, but in that unlikely case we’re talking about a dangerous inflationary spiral. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Higher prices are likely to result in lower unit sales, and thus in declining profit margins. My favorite economist (there’s an oxymoron for you), Conrad DeQuadros of Brean Capital, considers corporate profit margins to be the best leading indicator of recessions. When margins come under pressure, corporations stop making new investments and engage in layoffs and other forms of cost-cutting, often bringing on economic downturns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Economics is the science of choices and is fraught with trade-offs. That’s certainly true in the area of trade and tariffs. For example, it’s widely reported these days (I have no idea how reliably) that when tariffs were imposed on imported steel in 2018, 1,000 jobs were saved in the U.S. steel industry. But 75,000 jobs were lost (or potential new employees weren’t hired) in U.S. steel-using industries. How will these choices be made? Similarly, as I wrote in the memo &lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/economic-reality.pdf?sfvrsn=49bc1865_6" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Economic Reality&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in May 2016:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;How will the interests of the 3.2 million Americans estimated to have lost their manufacturing jobs to China be balanced against the hundreds of millions who would have to pay considerably more for imported goods? Not an easy question. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In all spheres of economic activity, the more uncertain people feel, the more reticent they are to bear risk. In the less certain world we may be facing, people are likely to be loath to make decisions and enter into agreements, and they’ll probably offer to pay less for a unit of profit potential. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Maynard Keynes described economic activity as being fed by “animal spirits,” which he described as “a spontaneous urge to action rather than inaction, and not as the outcome of a weighted average of quantitative benefits multiplied by quantitative probabilities” (per Wikipedia). The usual source of this urge is optimism, perhaps as reflected in consumer confidence. &lt;strong&gt;What will be the source of positive animal spirits in the environment that lies ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The International Picture &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The impact of the developments on tariffs extends importantly to the international arena and goes well beyond economics. Global trade has had an enormous beneficial effect on the entire world since the end of World War II. Along with expenditures to rebuild after the war, technological and managerial progress, improvements in infrastructure, and the expansion of capital markets, &lt;strong&gt;globalization contributed to a rising economic tide that truly lifted all boats.&lt;/strong&gt; Some countries and some people did better than others, of course, but virtually everyone was better off. I believe it was because of this, among other things, that we’ve generally enjoyed peace and prosperity for the last 80 years. &lt;strong&gt;As a result, we’ve been privileged to live in the best period in history.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main benefit from globalization is called “comparative advantage.” Every country has some things it produces better and/or cheaper, and others where the reverse is true. If every country makes the former products and sells them to the rest of the world, and buys the latter products from other countries, collective welfare is maximized thanks to increased overall efficiency. As I said on Bloomberg TV on Friday, we’re all better off because Italy makes the pasta and Switzerland makes the watches. But if trade barriers were to require Italy to make its own watches and Switzerland to make its own pasta, the citizens in both countries would probably end up paying more for products they used to buy cheaper from abroad, or consuming inferior products made locally, or both.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. citizens in particular have benefitted massively from the fact that most things can be made more cheaply in other countries – and especially developing nations – because wages are lower. This has cost the U.S. a few million jobs, but it has also allowed virtually all Americans to live much better than they would have if they had been limited to buying U.S.-made goods. That’s the simple reason why most of the non-food merchandise at Walmart is imported. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;To cite one more factor that has made the world a better place, &lt;strong&gt;I describe the behavior of the U.S. in the post-World War II period as “generosity toward the rest of the world stemming from enlightened self-interest.”&lt;/strong&gt; Under the Marshall Plan, we gave (not loaned) billions of dollars with which Western Europe rebuilt. Likewise, between 1945 and 1952, General Douglas MacArthur oversaw the reconstruction of Japan and the strengthening of its economy. Since then, the U.S. has (a) distributed extensive foreign aid, (b) invested heavily in healthcare in developing nations, (c) created programs that bring foreign students to the U.S. and vice versa, and (d) beamed positive messages to people throughout the world. These are all instances of generosity. In each “transaction,” we gave more than we directly got, and a cynic might say we acted like suckers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, these things can be described as largesse, but as the National Archive puts it, the Marshall Plan “provided markets for American goods, created reliable trading partners, and supported the development of stable democratic governments in Western Europe.” That’s a pretty good payoff. People in other countries received lots of freebies, but certainly these programs helped the U.S. by restraining communism, bringing nations into defensive alignment with the U.S., and contributing to the U.S.’s position as the world’s most prosperous nation. I have no interest in seeing the U.S. turn isolationist. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But it’s very possible we could throw this process into reverse: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can antagonize our trading partners and cause our allies to feel like they’re being bullied and extorted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can force countries that have depended on us for capital and other forms of assistance to look to China and Russia for these things instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can convince the rest of the world to invest less in the U.S. and less in U.S. Treasurys.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first two points could cost us important allies and cause nations to look less favorably on democracy. As my friend Michael Smith says, “You can’t antagonize and influence at the same time.” And the third point would dramatically influence the U.S.’s fiscal position.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;To date, the world’s high opinion of the U.S. economy, rule of law, and fiscal solidity has allowed us to hold a “golden credit card,” where there’s no credit limit and no bill ever comes. This enabled the U.S. to run fiscal deficits in each of the last 25 years and all but four of the last 45, including trillion-dollar-plus deficits in each of the last five years. &lt;strong&gt;In other words, we’ve been able to live beyond our means&lt;/strong&gt;, with the federal government spending more than it takes in via taxes and fees. This has led to one of the worst things about the U.S.: the $36 trillion national debt and the grossly irresponsible behavior in Washington that caused it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since I don’t expect Washington to suddenly begin to behave responsibly and live with balanced budgets, I’m left to wonder how much longer we can count on that golden credit card.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Might other countries become less willing to buy U.S. Treasurys? Might they conclude that our fiscal management is unreliable?
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even if we remain the world’s strongest credit, might they cut back on purchases out of worry, spite, or political motivation?
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What would happen if a Treasury auction failed? (I imagine the Fed would buy the unsold securities, but I’m uncomfortable about it creating the money to do so by crediting banks with deposits with which to buy. In the end, where does the money come from?)
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Will we remain the world’s strongest credit if the dollar comes to be less accepted as the world’s reserve currency?
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What would happen to the deficit – and thus the national debt – if buyers demand higher interest rates on Treasurys? To date, some of our trade deficits have probably been recycled into purchases of U.S. Treasurys. What happens to rates on Treasurys if that ceases?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Going all the way back to World War II and longer, the U.S. has been “holding the cards.” Trump believes in the strength of the U.S. and in cashing in on it. That’s what his moves on tariffs amount to: no longer “throwing the party” for the rest of the world. No longer generosity in the hope of long-term benefits, but rather transactions in which we extract fair value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve received a lot of kind responses to Friday’s appearance on Bloomberg TV, and I’m going to use a comment from a viewer to bring us to a conclusion on this subject:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 1980s, people like [Trump’s counselor for trade and manufacturing] Peter Navarro decided that Japan pulling ahead of the US in autos threatened the future of the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Japan did indeed pull ahead and never looked back.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. economy has more than doubled in size relative to Japan since then. It has doubled even after allowing for population changes and currency strength. It doubled in spite of losing the lead in autos, &lt;strong&gt;or is it that it doubled partly because of it?&lt;/strong&gt; The margins on computer software and jet engines are probably a good deal higher than on mass-market automobiles. (Emphasis added)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Japan exploited its advantages in producing autos, and the U.S. moved on to things in which it could achieve an advantage of its own. &lt;strong&gt;Isn’t that exactly the way things should work in a dynamic global economy? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As I asked in a memo in September, is it a good idea for governments to try to override the laws of economics in an effort to cause their economies – which if left alone would follow their own natural course – to satisfy policy preferences?&lt;/strong&gt; A tariff is an “externality” or “artificiality” designed to (a) discourage exports that would otherwise take place and thus (b) help domestic businesses make sales that wouldn’t take place if they were left to function on their own. What will be the cost, and who will bear it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bottom Line&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I consider the tariff developments thus far to be what soccer fans call an “own goal”&lt;/strong&gt; – a goal scored for the other side when a player accidentally puts the ball into his own team’s net. In this way, they’re highly analogous to Brexit, and we know how that turned out. Brexit cost the British mightily in terms of GDP, morale, and alliances, and it harmed their reputation for governance and stability. All of this damage was self-inflicted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I like the way things have gone during my lifetime&lt;/strong&gt;, which conveniently spans 99% of the post-war period I’ve been discussing. Some of our government expenditures have certainly been misspent, both at home and abroad, and our national debt is nothing to celebrate. But I’ve enjoyed living in a peaceful, prosperous, and increasingly healthy world, and I’m not eager to see that change. &lt;strong&gt;Just a couple of months ago, the U.S. economy was performing well, the outlook was positive, the stock market was at an all-time high, and there was much talk about American exceptionalism. Now, if Trump’s tariffs are put into effect, the U.S. economy is likely to experience a recession sooner than otherwise would have been the case, higher inflation, and extensive dislocation.&lt;/strong&gt; Even if the tariffs are reversed entirely, it’s unlikely the other nations will dismiss this incident and conclude that they have nothing to worry about in terms of relations with the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No one should rule out the achievement of some of the goals of tariffs listed above.&lt;/strong&gt; U.S. manufacturing could increase, bringing new jobs and more dependable supply chains. Our treatment in world trade could become fairer. And the Treasury’s take could increase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the other hand, some of the hoped-for benefits are probably beyond reach.&lt;/strong&gt; In particular, as for reducing our trade deficit, the U.S. is unlikely to ever buy less from other countries than they buy from us as long as the U.S. is bigger and more prosperous and thus has greater buying power. This will be especially true as long as our workers are better paid, meaning most U.S.-made goods cost more than goods produced elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hoped-for results might materialize, or the negative consequences might be felt, or some combination of the two. &lt;strong&gt;It must be borne in mind, however, that whereas the negative ramifications from tariffs will probably be felt almost immediately, any gains are likely to come only in the long run, following a multi-year period of adjustment. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;And what about the financial markets? In the last few days there’s been a massive shift in the economic outlook and a huge stock market decline in reaction. As always, the key question surrounds the appropriateness of the response to date: has it been just right, inadequate, or excessive? It’s even harder to answer that question than usual, since there can be little confidence that the economic world of the future won’t be significantly different from – and probably worse than the one we’ve lived in up to now. &lt;strong&gt;On the one hand, if the tariffs remain as announced and retaliation leads to an all-out trade war, the economic consequences could be truly dire. But on the other hand, cooler heads (and highly negative political and stock-market reactions) could prevail, causing the tariffs to be rolled back to less harmful levels, perhaps even leading to gains for free trade. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;How is the Fed likely to respond? The threat of recession might call for accelerated rate cuts to bolster economic activity. Or the threat of inflation might cause rates to stay higher, with cuts postponed. Note, however, that inflation-fighting measures such as higher rates are probably less likely to succeed against inflation caused by the addition of tariffs to selling prices than they would be against the more typical demand-driven inflation. Today’s title is particularly applicable to the Fed’s actions: certainly nobody knows. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Oaktree’s markets, fear of defaults (not unfounded) has caused risk compensation in the form of yield spreads to increase substantially, leading to a meaningful increase in the available yields on credit. At the same time, we anticipate a higher incidence of distress and increased demand for bespoke capital solutions, meaning we’re likely to invest our latest opportunistic debt fund faster than otherwise would have been the case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase Mark Twain, there are themes that rhyme throughout history. For that reason, just as I recycled the title of my post-Lehman bankruptcy memo for this one, I’ll also borrow its closing paragraph: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone was happy to buy 18-24-36 months ago, when the horizon was cloudless and asset prices were sky-high. Now, with heretofore unimaginable risks on the table and priced in, it’s appropriate to sniff around for bargains: the babies that are being thrown out with the bath water. We’re on the case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, I was fortunate to visit investors in Montreal on the day of the tariff announcement and in Toronto the day after. What a time for a trip to Canada! I started each meeting by saying I’m one of the hundreds of millions of Americans who respect Canada and consider it a friend and ally. The reception was stirring. &lt;strong&gt;This is a good time for all of us to connect with friends around the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April 9, 2025&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal Information and Disclosures&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum expresses the views of the author as of the date indicated and such views are subject to change without notice. Oaktree has no duty or obligation to update the information contained herein. Further, Oaktree makes no representation, and it should not be assumed, that past investment performance is an indication of future results. Moreover, wherever there is the potential for profit there is also the possibility of loss.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum is being made available for educational purposes only and should not be used for any other purpose. The information contained herein does not constitute and should not be construed as an offering of advisory services or an offer to sell or solicitation to buy any securities or related financial instruments in any jurisdiction. Certain information contained herein concerning economic trends and performance is based on or derived from information provided by independent third-party sources. Oaktree Capital Management, L.P. (“Oaktree”) believes that the sources from which such information has been obtained are reliable; however, it cannot guarantee the accuracy of such information and has not independently verified the accuracy or completeness of such information or the assumptions on which such information is based. &lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This memorandum, including the information contained herein, may not be copied, reproduced, republished, or posted in whole or in part, in any form without the prior written consent of Oaktree.&lt;/em&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;© 2025 Oaktree Capital Management, L.P.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
						
						
							
								

Share
 &lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again&amp;text=Oaktree Capital: Nobody Knows (Yet Again):%20https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/shareArticle?mini=true&amp;url=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again/%2F&amp;title=Oaktree Capital: Nobody Knows (Yet Again)&amp;summary=&amp;source=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again/%2F&amp;quote=Oaktree Capital: Nobody Knows (Yet Again)" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:?subject=Oaktree Capital: Nobody Knows (Yet Again)&amp;body=https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
								
							

						
					
				
			
		
	













	
		
			
				
					
						&lt;h2&gt;Related Content&lt;/h2&gt;
					
					
						
							
									&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo-podcast/nobody-knows-yet-again" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/hm_memo_podcast.png?sfvrsn=61247366_3" alt="Nobody Knows (Yet Again) for audio" /&gt;memosApr 9, 2025Nobody Knows (Yet Again)Listen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/insights/memo/the-pendulum-in-international-affairs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/hm-memos_written-image-1_530x299px.png?sfvrsn=50697366_3" alt="The Pendulum in International Affairs for article" /&gt;memosMar 23, 2022The Pendulum in International AffairsRead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/nobody-knows-ii.pdf?sfvrsn=108eb165_8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.oaktreecapital.com/images/oaktreecaplibraries/insights/memos/the-memo-from-howard-marksd198ddb3-6ceb-4922-8cac-9ddfca1ae261.png?sfvrsn=7bfc7366_1" alt="Nobody Knows II for article" /&gt;memosMar 3, 2020Nobody Knows IIRead&lt;/a&gt;


								
								
									
										
											Load More
										
									
								
							
						
					

				
			

		

	
	
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="javascript:openPDF('Nobody Knows (Yet Again)_JPN','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/translated-memos/nobody-knows-(yet-again)_jpn.pdf?sfvrsn=804e2b66_1')" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Download PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</content:encoded>
      <enclosure url="javascript:openPDF('Nobody Knows (Yet Again)_JPN','https://www.oaktreecapital.com/docs/default-source/memos/translated-memos/nobody-knows-(yet-again)_jpn.pdf?sfvrsn=804e2b66_1')" type="application/pdf"/>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>